<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Panacea Christiana, or, A Christians soueraigne salue for euery soare deliuered in two seuerall sermons, and now digested into one treatise : published for the vse of all distressed Christians.</title>
            <author>Herring, Theodore, 1596-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13203.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24562430</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24562430</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27779</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03078)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27779)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1853:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panacea Christiana, or, A Christians soueraigne salue for euery soare deliuered in two seuerall sermons, and now digested into one treatise : published for the vse of all distressed Christians.</title>
                  <author>Herring, Theodore, 1596-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 92, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Isaac Iaggard for Robert Bird, and are to be sold at his shop in Cheapeside at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The Epistle Dedicatory" signed: Th. Hering.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-G⁸.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans VIII, 28 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Panacea Chriſtiana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR A CHRISTIANS SOVERAIGNE SALVE FOR EVERY SOARE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DELI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERED</hi> In Two ſeuerall SERMONS, <hi>and now digeſted into one Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: publiſhed for the vſe of all diſtreſſed Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſaiah 50.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord hath giuen me a tongue of the Learned, that I ſhould know how to <hi>Miniſter</hi> a word in time to him that is weary.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>AVGVSTIN.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Tam bonus eſt Deus vt nullo modo permitteret ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum niſi inde noſſet elicere bonum.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iſaac Iaggard</hi> for <hi>Robert Bird,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Cheapeſide, at the Signe of the Bible. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Sir EDWARD COOKE, <hi>Knight, one of his Maieſties most Honourable Priuy Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides thoſe common enducements which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with others (your Honours more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary zeale and affection to Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Pietie) there are ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate obligations which haue moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to conſecrate the firſt fruits of my Labours, to your Patronage. It was their command, to whom I owe not obedience and reſpect on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:27779:3"/> but my-ſelfe alſo, that firſt expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe lines to the cenſure of the World, and then ſhrouded them vnder the ſhelter of your Winges. For the ſubiect matter,<note place="margin">Vtinam tam commodum quam acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum.</note> as it ſuites well with the times; ſo I preſume it will not bee vnwelcome to your Honour. A word in his place, as the Wiſeman obſerues) <hi>is like Apples of Gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25, 11.</note> 
               <hi>with pictures of Siluer.</hi> If this Theame bee not now ſeaſonable, when will it bee? The Church of God goes to wracke abroad: many miſeries and calamities preſſe vs ſore at home, &amp; our ſinnes threaten more and worſe. Satan rageth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his time is but ſhort; his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments flouriſh: the wicked are in their ruffe, the godly vnderfoot, deſpiſed, trampled vpon. The old complaint is not vniuſtly renewed, that it fals out, <hi>Bonis malè, malis benè,
<pb facs="tcp:27779:3"/> Well with the Bad, ill with the Good.</hi> Is it not now high time to miniſter a word of comfort to them <hi>that mourn in Sion?</hi> What greater comfort then this Oracle from Heauen; <hi>All ſhall worke to the Beſt of them that loue God?</hi> Of which number, the Church of God hath good cauſe to eſteeme your Honor, who haue taſted with your Brethren, this <hi>bitter Cup,</hi> and therefore can relliſh theſe <hi>Sweetes</hi> the better. For my part, I know not how to teſtifie my reſpects other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then in theſe kind of Preſents, and my hearty prayers for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of your Honour and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which ſhal neuer be wanting from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors moſt humble obſeruance,</hi> Th: Hering.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader;</hi> This ſmal Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate was ſo penned, as Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; and ſo Preached, as thou mayeſt eaſily gueſſe, it was neuer inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for oſtentation, but for aedification. Jf thou look'st for many Citations and Quotations of <hi>Authors,</hi> thou deceyuest thy Selfe. It was my Ambition (J con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) to draw water out of the fountains, rather then out of the ſtreames. <hi>Dulcius ex ipſo fonte bibuntur aquae.</hi> Man purpoſeth, but God dispoſeth. The truth is, violence and importunity wrung this for the Preſſe, which was intended ſoly for the Pulpit. I know there is great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene a liuing vice, and a dead Letter, as betweene a body anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and a painted body. I know this Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and Cenſorious Age, will giue but
<pb facs="tcp:27779:5"/> harſh entertainment to ſuch a rude and vnpoliſhed <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and deeme it more fit to be ſuppreſſed in a corner, then to be publiſhed to the World; yet my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, A <hi>Widdowes Mite</hi> will find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation with the Searcher of the heart. Beſides, J had rather ſeeme too forward in putting out my Maſters money to the Bankers, then to vndergo the Doome of an euill Seruant, for ſmothering his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in a Napkin. All Starres are not of the ſame magnitude, yet euery Starre ſhines in his owne Orbe. If ſome beames of Comfort conueyghed in theſe curſorie Meditations, may warme and enliuen any poore drooping diſconſolate Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, J haue my ayme, let God haue the Honour and Glory. As <hi>all things,</hi> ſo this (J hope) <hi>ſhall worke to the Beſt.</hi> Read, and conſider. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27779:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Panacea Chriſtiana.</hi> OR A CHRISTIANS ſoueraigne Salue for euery Sore.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 8.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For wee know that all things worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good, to them that loue God, to them who are the called ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his purpoſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Oweuer the whole Scripture (as S.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to his Scholler <hi>Timothy</hi>) be giuen by diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, and is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, to teach, to improue, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27779:6"/> that the man of God, may be made perfect to all good workes. Yet as in the large <hi>folio</hi> of the booke of <hi>Nature,</hi> though euery Creature car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it the ſparkles of the power, goodneſſe, and prouidence of the Creator; thoſe <hi>rayes</hi> ſhine out more brightly in ſome, more dimmely in others; ſo in the leſſer <hi>Epitome</hi> of the Scripture, albeit all the parcels of ſacred Writ, breath forth one and the ſelfe-ſame diuine truth in a moſt ſweete and heauenly harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; yet in ſome paſſages the Spirit of God takes to himſelfe (as it were) the winges of an <hi>Eagle,</hi> ſoaring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft aboue the capacity of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: in others he creepes (as it were) on the ground, ſtooping to the ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low conceit of the meaneſt. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he couers himſelfe with thick clouds,<note place="margin">Pſ. 8.18, 12.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; darknes is his Pauillion;</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whiles he ſpeaks to vs familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Exod. 33, 11.</note> as to his ſeruant <hi>Moſes, face to face,</hi> mouth to mouth. The new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament by the conſent of all, in this reſpect carries the preheminence beyond the old. <hi>The gloſſe muſt bee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27779:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> clearer then the text.</hi> Among the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Paul</hi> outſtrips his fellowes; who for his labour, or his learning, was euer held the <hi>chiefeſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi> Among the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> his to the <hi>Romans</hi> (if ſuch invaluable <hi>Iewels</hi> may be valued one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if one <hi>ſtar</hi> may differ from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in glory) bears the name from the reſt; whether we reſpect doctrin of <hi>faith, or good manners, matter of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, or exhortation, of confutation or conſolation;</hi> ſo largely diſcuſſed, ſo pithily preſſed, ſo wiſely managed. In this Epiſtle, this chap. is of moſt admirable vſe: being placed as the Sun in the midſt of the Firmament, and containing in it a rich Mine of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation. In this chap. this verſe is placed as the heart in the midſt of the body, that giues life to all the members. There are two profeſſed enemies which lay perpetual <hi>ſiege</hi> to the bulwarke of true Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: <hi>Sinne and Affliction.</hi> Theſe like troubleſome gueſts, and vnwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Inmates,</hi> ſo diſturbe the peace of the <hi>Saints,</hi> while they lodge in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27779:7"/> theſe cottages of clay, that it makes them weary of their houſes, and themſelues to, putting them oft to <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> complaint,<note place="margin">Gen. 27.46.</note> 
               <hi>Would to God I were dead.</hi> Theſe are thoſe <hi>Sana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites</hi> and <hi>Hittites</hi> which are perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>goades</hi> in their ſides, perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>prickes</hi> in their eyes.<note place="margin">Numb. 33.55</note> Here is that Gall and Wormwood which embitters all the ſweets this world can affoord. To ſhut vp in a word, here is that <hi>Coloquintida</hi> which matres the other herbes, and makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that taſts cry,<note place="margin">Mors in Olla. <hi>2. Kings. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.40</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Death is the pot.</hi> Againſt both theſe, <hi>Paul</hi> addreſſes his diſcourſe in this chapter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in like a valiant champion, expert in the Lords battailes, hauing muſtred vp his forces, and marſhalled them in battaile array, in the Fore-front, he affronts ſinne, <hi>the head of this Serpent,</hi> in the Rereward, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters with Affliction, <hi>the taile of this Serpent,</hi> the after a long skirmiſh, wins the field, and ſounds the Triumph; <hi>Neither life nor death, things preſent, nor things to come, ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of God in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27779:7"/> Chriſt.</hi> More plainely, here is an <hi>Antidote,</hi> a <hi>Cordiall</hi> propoſed an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the poyſon of ſin; a <hi>Cordiall</hi> againſt the anguiſh of the croſſe. The Antidote againſt ſin is propounded, verſe 1. confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med verſe 2. proſecuted, applyed in the ſequel to verſe 17. The Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als to mittigate the anguiſh of the croſſe, are threefold. The firſt is, drawne from the end of it, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Chriſt verſe 17. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond from the guide we haue in it, <hi>the Spirite helpeth <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> infirmities,</hi> verſe 26. The third is taken from the good iſſue wee ſhall haue out of it, verſe 28. So that theſe words carry in them, a ſoueraigne Cordial againſt all miſeries, croſſes, calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whatſoeuer, whereſoeuer, how many, how great ſoeuer, which may or ſhall vex the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, while they ſoiourne in <hi>this valley of teares, and vale of miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In treating heereof (that I may acquaint you with my method) we with conſider the connexion firſt, then the propoſition. In the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27779:8"/> the <hi>Circumſtance, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is obſerueable.</hi> The Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances will lead vs into the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the perſons to whom this <hi>Cordiall</hi> is intended reſtrained; <hi>(We)</hi> of the manner how it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, euidently, confidently <hi>(Wee know:)</hi> for the ſubſtance in it you haue firſt the generality <hi>(all things)</hi> then the Harmony, <hi>(worke together:)</hi> thirdly, the ſcope or drift of their working <hi>(for good:)</hi> laſtly, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the parties whom this concerns, from their inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>(they that loue God)</hi> from their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual vocation <hi>(that they are called <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of God:)</hi> from their eternall election <hi>(that they are called according to his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> purpoſe.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the rude lineaments of our preſent diſcourſe, which wee intend (by <hi>the Diuine Aſsiſtance</hi>) to proſecute and polliſh ouer with a ſecond, &amp; more accurate draught. That which firſt offers it ſelfe to our Meditation, is the Connexion, which ſhall bee diſpatched in a word <hi>(Alſo:)</hi> this copulatiue particle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27779:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> like ſome corner ſtone in a curious ſtructure, knits this verſe to the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes immediately preceding; as if the Apoſtle had deliuered himſelfe more plainely and fully. If this be not ſufficient to ſtrengthen your <hi>feeble knees,</hi> to erect your deiected ſpirits; that ſuffering is the way to glory, that by the <hi>Croſſe</hi> you doe but climbe to this <hi>Crowne;</hi> that Mount <hi>Caluary</hi> lies onely in the rhode to Mount <hi>Tabor;</hi> that heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſtands your <hi>conformitie to him, vvho vvas conſecrated your High-Prieſt by Affliction.</hi> If the ſweete meditation of the glorie to come, cannot digeſt the preſent bitterneſſe of the Croſſe; if the preſence, the aſſiſtance of that <hi>Spirit of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that <hi>Comforter,</hi> who is <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort it ſelfe,</hi> cannot cheare your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolated ſpirits, nor aſſwage your ſorrow; adde to the former heape a ſerious meditation of the power &amp; ouer-ruling Prouidence of your heauenly Father, whereby all things are ſo wiſely diſpoſed, ſo ſweetly carried, ſo cunningly contriued,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27779:9"/> that what-euer happens in the world, all worke together for the beſt of them that loue God, &amp;c. All things and among the reſt your afflictions which are ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicing your fatuation, that they aduance it; ſo farre from being (as your deeme in your weake diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers) <hi>clogges</hi> to wedge you to the earth, that they proue after a ſort as <hi>wings,</hi> whereby you ſoare aloft to heauen: ſo farre from being <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la inferni,</hi> a p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acipice from whence your ſoules ſhould bee tumbled headlong into the infernall Lake, that indeed they proue to be a <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la coeli,</hi> a <hi>Iaakobs ladder,</hi> vpon whoſe ſtaires the Angels of God are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually aſcending and deſcending, by which ſteps the Elect mount in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abrams,</hi> boſome. Theſe tall <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nakims</hi> ſerue not to tread you as mire vnder their feete, but to lift you vp (as Kings and Princes) vpon their ſhoulders neerer heauen. He that hath but halfe an eye, may now ſee the drift of the Apoſtle, which is to reach foorth a ſtrong
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27779:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Cable of Conſolation;</hi> vnto thoſe poore Saints and ſeruants of God; who ſayling in the troubleſome Sea of this tumultuous world, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing encountred with great ſtorms, and now almoſt ouer-whelmed with the ſucceſſion of many hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous waues one preſſing on another; are labouring for life, ready to be plunged into the gulfe of deſpaire. A ſtrong Cable it is, compoſed of many threds, ſo twiſted together, that all the Diuels in hell ſhall neuer be able to breake it.<note place="margin">Eccle. 4.9.12</note> 
               <hi>Two</hi> (ſayth <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) are better then one:</hi> a threefold cord cannot eaſily be broken. In that our Apoſtle contents not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with one Argument of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, but to the firſt addes a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and ſtrengthens the ſecond with a third; the obſeruation is plaine and euident. As, <hi>many are the Croſſes of the Righteous;</hi> so, <hi>their Comforts are many;</hi> the Afflictions of the iuſt goe not ſingle, but by throngs &amp; troopes: one following on the neck, one treading vpon the heele of another: <hi>Velus vnda vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:27779:10"/> as waues ſeconds waue in the Sea; neither are their conſolations ſingle. Loe here is a double, nay a trebble ground of ſolid comfort;<note place="margin">Pſal. 34, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Many are the troubles of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but the Lord will deliuer them out of all.</hi> Many troubles, many deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerances; ſo many troubles, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deliuerances; euery ſeuerall trouble hath a ſeuerall reſcue, till he be deliuered, not from ſome, or from few, or from many, but from al. Euery proper temptation hath it owne proper iſſue. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 15. So <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.21. Looke how many <hi>hornes</hi> were raiſed to puſh at the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> of God, ſo many Carpenters were appointed, ſo many hammers lifted vp to breake thoſe hornes in pieces.<note place="margin">Iohn. 16, 33.</note> 
               <hi>In the world you ſhall haue trouble;</hi> (there's the croſſe.) <hi>In me you ſhall haue peace;</hi> there's the comfort.<note place="margin">Act. 14, 22,</note> 
               <hi>Through many tribulations you muſt enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi> Tribulations, many Tribulations; there's many croſſes; theſe tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions miniſter a paſſage by which we get heauen; there's many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27779:10"/> if with <hi>Paul</hi> wee <hi>haue terrors without, and terrors within,</hi> we ſhal finde comforts without and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts within: if we be diſtreſſed on all ſides with him, with him wee ſhall be comforted on all ſides. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to this purpoſe is that of the ſame Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 9. <hi>We are afflicted on euery ſide:</hi> there's croſſe vpon croſſe: <hi>yet not in diſtreſſe,</hi> there's comfort. Hee goes on, <hi>wee are in doubt, but deſpaire not: we are perſecuted, but not forſaken, caſt downe, but wee periſh not, &amp;c.</hi> It is very remarkable to obſerue how the croſſes &amp; comforts, with which that choſen veſſell was <hi>laded, poiſed,</hi> and <hi>ballanced</hi> each other: yet in the end, verſe 17. the comfort infinitely weighs downe the croſſe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cals it <hi>a light affliction, but a weight of glory.</hi> Let mee ſhut vp the proofe of this point with the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonema</hi> of the ſame Apoſtle.<note place="margin">2, Cor. 1,3.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bee the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who comforts vs in all our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, that as our ſuffering for Chriſt hath abounded, ſo our ioy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27779:11"/> might abound much more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You haue ſeene God doing his part: our parts now muſt follow. This ſerues (that I may deſcend fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the confirmation of the point vnto application, which is the life of all teaching) to miniſter matter of Thankfulneſſe, of Inſtruction, of Meditation. Of Thankfulnes firſt. How ſhould euery Chriſtians hart be rauiſhed with this conſideration and tranſported euen beyond it ſelfe, with the gratefull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of ſo high a fauour? The God of Conſolation is no niggard of his <hi>Cordials;</hi> he pinches not, he ſpares not, but giues vs into our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a good <hi>treaſure ſhaken toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſſed downe,</hi> running ouer &amp; wilt thou ſhow thy ſelfe a niggard in the retribution of Thankes? Is Gods hand opened &amp; thine ſhut? Is Gods heart enlarged and are thy bowels ſtrained? Shall the Creator giue vnto the Creature a <hi>Cup</hi> of Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, a <hi>Cup</hi> brimfull an ouer-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Cup,</hi> and ſhall not the Creature take vp (with the Princely Prophet)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27779:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>the cup of ſaluation? Will ye thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Lord, O ye fooliſh people and vnthankfull? Si ingratum dixeris omnia dixeris. Giue vnto the Lord all ye his Saints; Giue vnto the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 29.1.</note> What will you giue? <hi>thankes:</hi> what leſſe can ye giue? not verball only, but reall; not in word alone, but in deed and in truth, as the Apoſtle wiſhes the <hi>Epheſians to walke worthy of their vocation:</hi> ſuch is my counſel to all that haue taſted of this ſweete marrow and fatneſſe;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Walke worthy of ſo great Conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſerues ſecondly, for inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to make vs enamored with the booke of God, that rich <hi>wardrobe,</hi> and aboundant ſtore-houſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine comforts. <hi>If any be merry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>let him ſing Pſalmes, if afflicted let him pray,</hi> and read too. Whether ſhould wee go for light but to the Sunne?<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> for water but to the Wel-head? Lo here is that fountaine of conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>As the Hart brayeth after the riuers of water,</hi> ſo let thy diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated ſoule pant and thirſt after theſe Chriſtall ſtreames of liuing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27779:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> water,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.4.</note> which iſſuing from the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of the Sanctuary, <hi>makes glad the Citty of our God</hi> Heere bee thoſe <hi>Apples of Paradiſe, thoſe flag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of Wine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.5.</note> the true <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> which can fetch vs againe in our deepeſt <hi>ſwoundes,</hi> which alone can refreſh vs in our greateſt <hi>Agonies.</hi> Heere is the oyle of gladneſſe, the <hi>balme of Gilead;</hi> heere wee may ſucke, and be delighted; heere wee may milke and be ſatisfied. As for all other waters, either they are but ſtreames iſſuing from this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; howeuer pure in the head, yet may bee corrupted in the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels or <hi>pipes</hi> through which they are conueyed vnto vs: or if they flow from any other <hi>ſpring,</hi> they are not liuing, but dead waters: not ſweete but bitter ſtreames, <hi>corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not comforting</hi> the bowels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which they deſcend. All theſe comforters <hi>are miſerable comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Phiſitians of no value,</hi> drugges of no vertue. Theſe ſacred volumes are not vnfitly reſembled by one of the <hi>Ancients,</hi> to an Apothecaries
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27779:12"/> ſhop, richly furniſhed with ſalues for euery ſore, with receits and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies for euery malady. Our care and wiſedome muſt induce vs ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly to acquaint our ſelues with the ſeuerall compoſitions, that in all our extremities, we may be able on a ſodaine to fetch and cull out pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>salues</hi> for any <hi>ſores;</hi> fit receites againſt any diſtemper.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.92.</note> 
               <hi>I had fainted in my affliction</hi> (ſaith the Princely Prophet) <hi>if thy word had not ſtayed me vp.</hi> A wiſe man will haue his plaiſter ready, though his head bee not broken as yet.</p>
            <p>The laſt vſe ſerues for meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If there bee ſuch ſtore of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts ſuggeſted to vs on earth, what thinke you is reſerued for vs in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? The greateſt meaſure of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation we can haue here, is nothing in compariſon of what wee ſhall haue ther. The diſproportion is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not infinite: heere wee haue but the <hi>firſt fruites,</hi> there is the <hi>harueſt;</hi> here our comfort is but in the <hi>ſeed,</hi> there is the <hi>full croppe;</hi> heere wee haue but the <hi>earneſt,</hi> there is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27779:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> heere but a few ſparkles, there is the flame; heere but a few drops, there is the Ocean. Now it is diſtilled into our narrow mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed bottle, as we are capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, drop after drop; then wee ſhall bee <hi>bathed;</hi> yea, <hi>drenched</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer head and eares in a Sea of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. This ioy is ſo great, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into vs, but wee muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it.<note place="margin">Mar. 25.21.</note> So much that phraſe of ſpeech implyes: <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſeruant, enter into thy maſters ioy.</hi> There is fulneſſe of ioy, there are riuers of pleaſures for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore: ſuch comforts as eie hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer can the heart of man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue; Lord, <hi>Giue vs euermore of this Comfort.</hi> So much, if not too much of the connexion. We come now to the words in themſelues conſidered; where the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces firſt offer themſelues to our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation: the firſt is, the perſon to whom this priuiledge is entailed; <hi>(wee.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee that are made partakers of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27779:13"/> the Diuine nature; <hi>wee</hi> that are borne not of water but of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; <hi>Wee</hi> that are aduanced to bee a holy Nation; a peculiar people, a Royall Prieſt-hood: <hi>We</hi> that haue taſted of the bitter waters of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, We know &amp;c.</hi> There lies a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Emphaſis, (if you marke it) in this particle Wee; it is a word of reſtraint, and ſhuts vp the doore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all carnall. Wordlings; and will not allow them the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo Diuine truth. This Chriſtian <hi>Aphoriſme</hi> cannot bee conceiued; much leſſe embraced, much leſſe digeſted by a Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt. Wiſedome hath hid theſe things from the <hi>Wiſe of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 10.21.</note> 
               <hi>and reuealed them vnto Babes, and Sucklings:</hi> to ſuch Babes are deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that they may grow thereby. The naturall man perceiueth not the things of God; neither indeed can hee: So <hi>Paule,</hi> 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2.14. He percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not the things of God: there is his inability; neither can hee, there is an vtter impoſſibility. As ſoone
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27779:14"/> may a bruite beaſt conceiue, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe, reaſon, and diſcourſe of the things of men, as a man in his meer naturals, comprehend the things of God. <hi>This knowledge is beyond the ſphere of Nature;</hi> and wee are guided to it by a higher principle. This is one of thoſe <hi>deepe myſteries of Godlineſſe, into which the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels deſire to pry; an vnwiſe man knoweth it not, a foole cannot vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Celeſtiall thoughts, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend his dull capacity: tell a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <hi>Peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 4.7. 1. Pet. 1.8.</note> mind him of a <hi>ioy which is glorious and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable:</hi> aſſure him, there is a royall priuiledge peculiar to the choſen of God; that <hi>All things ſhall worke together to the beſt of them that loue God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.18. Act. 20.24.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You ſhal ſeeme to him a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> or (as the <hi>Athenians</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured <hi>Paule.</hi>) you muſt paſſe for a <hi>babler and broacher of new Doctrine;</hi> nay, <hi>Feſtus verdict</hi> will be your lot, <hi>much Deuotion hath made thee mad.</hi> If hee himſelfe diſcourſe of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27779:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> them, it is but Parrot-like, he ſpeaks by rote, he know's not what; vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Sentence, when he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not the ſenſe. Let his <hi>Wine and Oyle encreaſe;</hi> Let <hi>his Cowes Calue and ceaſe not;</hi> Let <hi>him haue his portion in this life, Eſaus Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> the fatnes of the earth, &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of bread; like the <hi>Cocke</hi> in the Fable hee will preferre one <hi>Barley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne</hi> before the richeſt <hi>Iewell</hi> which the earth can afford. Giue him Hay, Prouender, Huskes, and Acornes, the <hi>Leekes and Onions</hi> of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> he will not ſticke to bid much good may your Spirituall conſolations do you; let mee inioy the preſent comforts of this life: I ſhall neither enuy your hopes for the future, nor deſire them. Let me haue the <hi>Res,</hi> the poſſeſſion and fruition of my deſires, take you the <hi>Spes,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of I know not what <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Mountaines,</hi> which your crackt braines promiſe to themſelues. <hi>One Bird in the hand, is better then two in the buſh.</hi> As our Sauiour ſpake ſometimes to the woman of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:27779:15"/> if thou kneweſt the gift of God,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.10.</note> and who it is that ſpeaketh vnto thee, thou wouldſt haue asked &amp; be would haue giuen vnto thee of the water of the Well of life to drinke freely. So ſay I vnto thee, O thou ſilly ſottiſh <hi>Muck-worme,</hi> if thou couldſt but taſt the delicacy of this <hi>hid Manna,</hi> this Angelicall prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this ſuper-coeleſtiall and ſoule-rauiſhing conſolation, with which the Righteous Man is dayly, houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſolaced; how wouldſt thou loath the dirt and dung of this world?<note place="margin">2. Sam. 23.16.</note> How wouldſt thou (with <hi>Davids</hi> Worthyes) breake thorough a <hi>whole hoaſt of Philiſtims</hi> to get but a few drops of the water of this <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel;</hi> which now is powred forth vnto thee (as it were) by <hi>pale-fuls,</hi> and thou ſuffereſt it to bee ſpilt on the ground; nay, trampleſt it as mire and dirt vnder thy feete. But what do I waſting my ſpirits, and abuſing your patience, while I direct my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the <hi>belly, which hath no eares?</hi> I will now addreſſe my ſelfe to the hungry empty ſoule. Is there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27779:15"/> any heere whoſe bowels are kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, whoſe affections are enflamed? Is there any, that longs to haue a ſhare in this ineſtimable Treature? That longs to ſip of this cup? I know no ſurer way, no better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell can bee giuen him, then to inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt himſelfe in the <hi>ſociety of the Saints.</hi> Labour to bee of that <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion;</hi> bee one of that <hi>Incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and this praerogatiue granted to them, will not bee denyed to thee. If thou bee involued in this <hi>(We)</hi> if made partakers of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature, thou ſhalt bee made partakers of this diuine Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Saints are indeed the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true <hi>Good-fellowes</hi> which haue all things common. This <hi>(Wee)</hi> is not onely an <hi>excluſiue</hi> particle, to ſhut the doore againſt the wicked and prophane hand that would be ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at theſe dainty morſels, but alſo an <hi>incluſiue</hi> particle, opening the doore wide to the feeble hand of all weake palſie Chriſtians; for whom God hath ſpred this <hi>Table,</hi> furniſhings it euen in the wildernes.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27779:16"/> Leaſt any ſhould thinke this Table common for all commers, tagge and ragge: <hi>Paule</hi> appropriates it, points vs to the gueſt inuited, <hi>(We, and wee onely:)</hi> Leaſt any ſhould thinke this Table proper to <hi>Paule</hi> onely; hee enlargeth himſelfe to ſhew how it is common to all Chriſtians: <hi>(Wee, and all Wee.)</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto of the parties to whom this truth is intended and entailed; it is more then high time that wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the manner how it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, implyed in the next word <hi>(Know.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Wee know:)</hi> a word that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports both the perſpicuity and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety of this diuine <hi>Aphoriſme.</hi> This knowledge was no bare <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation,</hi> but a practicall <hi>obſeruation;</hi> not a meere Notion or naked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the braine, but a well grounded and ſetled perſwaſion of the heart. <hi>Wee know</hi> not theori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally onely, but really; not ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely onely, but experimentally; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, euery moment is this Scripture fulfilled in vs, and vpon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27779:16"/> vs, that <hi>all things worke, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>(we know)</hi> that is; we may know it, we muſt know it, we ſhall know it <hi>We may know,</hi> if we doe not wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhut our eyes; if we do but care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerue the carriage of God towards our ſelues, or any of the Saints, trace him in all his paſſages, you may eaſily ſent out the print of his footſteppes; <hi>Things reuealed, belong to vs and our Children. Wee ought, we muſt know it.</hi> Euery trade and profeſſion of life, Cittizens, Schollers, Souldiers: the Gentry, Comminalty, Nobility, haue cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain prerogatiues annexed to them (not to touch vppon the higheſt ranke.) What man ſo ſimple, as to bee ignorant of thoſe priuiledges which are granted by cuſtome or fauour to the meaneſt occupation? What a ſhame were it then for any profeſſed Chriſtian to bee vtterly vnacquainted with ſo maine a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge proper only to thoſe of that coate? <hi>Proprium Quarto modo</hi> (as Schoolemen deliuer it) <hi>omni Soli ſemper.</hi> Agreeing to <hi>all</hi> Chriſtians,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27779:17"/> 
               <hi>onely</hi> to a Chriſtian, and to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>alwayes.</hi> Nay, <hi>We ſhall know it.</hi> How euer in the times of our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance it may be hid from our eyes, that we cannot conceyue it; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer in the time of temptation, our hearts may be ſo vnſetled, that we cannot but doubt of it, yet ſooner or later, firſt or laſt, we ſhall attaine to this <hi>plerophory</hi> of our Apoſtle, we ſhall ſee clearly, beleeue confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and acknowledge feelingly, that <hi>All things worke together, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Myſterie</hi> is not reuealed ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the firſt daſh. The bright luſtre of ſo glorious a light, if it ſhould ſodainly breake out vpon us, would doubtleſſe dazle our dim <hi>Owlet</hi> eie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight. We ſee it firſt darkely as in a cloud, confuſedly (as it were) a far off in proceſſe of time, more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more diſtinctly, as yeares and experience ſhould teach an aged Scholler.</p>
            <p>The reaſon heereof is euident. This Knowledge is the <hi>Mother</hi> of all ſpirituall <hi>Courage, Conſtancie, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> and <hi>Perſeuerance.</hi> This is the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27779:17"/> wiſe mans <hi>harbour,</hi> which ſecures him in the greateſt ſtormes. What though the earth be mooued? What though the <hi>Sea rore &amp; make a noyſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.2.3</note> 
               <hi>The mountaines be tumbled into the middeſt of the Sea?</hi> What though the whole world bee in a tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vprore, running into a <hi>Chaos of Confuſion?</hi> That heart which hath planted it ſelfe on this <hi>Rocke,</hi> is no whit affraid of euill tydings, ſtands as <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> which cannot bee moued. Why? It knowes that wiſe <hi>Pilot</hi> which ſits aboue, does not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee whateuer fals out in the <hi>glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy Sea of this world</hi> (amiddeſt all the weltrings and changes of the ſame) but ſo diſpoſes of euery particular accident, that it turnes to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good of his ſeruants. The <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant venturer</hi> puts to Sea, rides out many a bitter ſtorme, runnes many a deſperat hazard, vpon hope of a gainfull returne. The <hi>ſtout Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier;</hi> takes his life into his hand, runnes vpon the mouth of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, dares <hi>the Lyon his owne Den</hi> vpon hope of victory. Euery man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27779:18"/> hazards in his calling, yet are but vncertaine Venturers, ignorant of the iſſue. The <hi>Greedy Aduenturer,</hi> ſeeking to encreaſe his ſtocke, loſes many times both it, and himſelfe. The <hi>Couetous Souldier,</hi> gaping after ſpoyle and victory, finds himſelfe ſpoyled, captiuated. But the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian runnes not at vncertaine, he is ſure of the <hi>goale</hi> when he ſets forth. We are ſure of the <hi>day</hi> before wee enter into the <hi>field:</hi> we may <hi>ante vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorian Triumpham canere, ſound the Triumph before the victory.</hi> When we put on our <hi>harneſſe,</hi> wee dare boaſt as he that puts it off before a ſtroke be ſtricken. We know wee ſhall be <hi>more then Conquerours, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> What made that ſtripling <hi>Dauid</hi> (that Noble &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine <hi>Sparke</hi> of Magnanimity) runne haſtily to encounter with that <hi>Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantean</hi> Monſter,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17, 37</note> 
               <hi>Goliah?</hi> He <hi>knew Iehouah</hi> would cloſe his Enemy in his hand? What whetted <hi>Gedeons valour</hi> to march on ſo boldly with a handfull of men, and a few <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pitchers,</hi> againſt ſo numerous
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27779:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> an hoaſt of armed <hi>Midianites?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudges 7, 15.</note> He <hi>knew</hi> the euent, God aſſured him of <hi>victory.</hi> What encoraged the three Children, and ſo animated them, that they ran as willingly into the <hi>hot fiery Furnace,</hi> as it were to a <hi>bed of Doune, or Roſes?</hi> They <hi>knew</hi> theyr God was able to deliuer them.<note place="margin">Dan. 3, 17.</note> Why ſhould we then be affraide (if our Lord and Maſter call vs forth) to grapple with the <hi>Goliah of Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> to encounter with a whole <hi>hoaſt of croſſes,</hi> to drinke of the bitter water of <hi>Marah,</hi> or to vndergo the <hi>fiery Tryall?</hi> Lord <hi>ſtrengthen our faith, that we quaile not in the day of Battell, but rather by that Eagle eye, piercing through the vncomfortable miſtes and clouds of Affliction, we may behold that comfortable cloſe, how this bloud-red Sea ſhall but miniſter to vs a paſſage to our heauenly Canaan</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my iuſt indignation, if in the falling off from this point, I fal foul upon thoſe freſh-watered &amp; white liuer'd <hi>Souldiers,</hi> who ſailing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rough ſeas of this World, are <hi>gaſhed</hi> with euery ſtorme, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27779:19"/> frighted with euery <hi>guſt.</hi> The leaſt apparant danger ſettes them quite beſides themſelues, &amp; driues them into <hi>Dauids</hi> diſſident concluſion; <hi>I ſaid in my haſt all men are lyars:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.11.</note> Or makes them cry out with <hi>Peter, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſaue me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 14.30.</note> 
               <hi>I periſh.</hi> Whence this? but becauſe we look only <hi>on things which are ſeene, not on things vvhich are not ſeene;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.18.</note> becauſe wee liue by ſight and ſenſe, not by faith. <hi>(Hinc illae lachrymae.)</hi> Hence thoſe feares, thoſe feares, thoſe vnlawfull ſhifts plotted and practiſed to wind our ſelues out of ſuch greeuous perple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xities. Theſe haue no faith, or at beſt are but men of little faith, as our Sauiour increpates his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.26.</note> if their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were come to full growth to a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: they wold doubtleſſe ſtand ſtill and <hi>behold the ſaluation of the Lord.</hi> They wold ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>we know that al things &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus are we falne ere wee are aware, into the <hi>body</hi> of our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, theſe <hi>Skirts and Subburbes</hi> haue led vs into the <hi>heart</hi> of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If any thinke I haue dwelt too
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27779:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> long in the <hi>Portall,</hi> let this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent them, we are now in the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace:</hi> we haue beene long in crac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſhell, that your appetites might bee whetted to <hi>long</hi> for the kernell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(All things:)</hi> Now, few not many, but <hi>(All)</hi> none excepted <hi>(worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.)</hi> Many and ſundry Agents are found in the world, whoſe courſe and ſcope, whoſe aime and ends, and actions are not the ſame; they communicate not their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets each to other; yea, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are <hi>diuers;</hi> nay <hi>aduerſe,</hi> one thwarting, croſſiing another; yet the ouer-ruling <hi>Prouidence</hi> of that <hi>ſupreme Moderator and ſole Monarch of Heauen and earth,</hi> ſo ſwaies all ſubordinate and inferior inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that in the midſt of their mutuall iarres and oppoſitions, they conſpire in a ſacred <hi>Harmony;</hi> as if they were entred into a <hi>holy league,</hi> or ſome <hi>ſacred combination</hi> for the good of his choſen: where euer they be in reſpect of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſoeuer in regard of their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27779:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> perſons, howſoeuer diſ-ioynted in regard of their affections; all their proiects and practices <hi>tend</hi> or ſhall <hi>turne</hi> to the good of the Elect. If I were diſcourſing among <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> me thinks they might excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently be ſhadowed out by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution of the Heauens.</hi> Euery <hi>Planet</hi> moues in it owne proper <hi>Orbe;</hi> their motions are not all alike, but vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; nay, oppoſite each vnto other. Hence thoſe different <hi>Coniunctions, Oppoſitions, and Aſpects, of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets;</hi> yet by the wheeling round of the <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> they are brought about to one determinate point. If I were to diſcourſe among <hi>Stateſ-men;</hi> I would wiſh them to obſerue the wiſe and politicke car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of a <hi>Prouident Prince;</hi> who meeting with <hi>oppoſite factions</hi> in his State, while each man takes his owne way, one ſeeking to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine another; he ſerues his owne endes, of both ſo wiſely managing the good, ſo powerfully ouer-aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bad, that all turnes to the common good: I leaue the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27779:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the iudicious Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(For good:)</hi> ſo ſome Interpreters; for the <hi>Beſt</hi> ſo others: the former expoſition is good and warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; the latter, I take is <hi>Beſt</hi> and moſt <hi>Emphaticall.</hi> There is a foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>good</hi> incident to mankinde; <hi>Naturall, Ciuill, Spirituall, Eternall. Naturall,</hi> which reſpects the good of our bodies; the <hi>Ciuill,</hi> the good of our ſtates; <hi>Spirituall,</hi> the good of our ſoules in this life <hi>Eternall;</hi> the happineſſe of body and ſoule both in the life to come. The <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall good</hi> is common to man and beaſt; the <hi>Ciuill</hi> is common to the wicked with the Godly; onely the <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>Eternall,</hi> aduances the righteous as much aboue the prophane, as the <hi>Ciuill</hi> aduances a Man aboue a Beaſt. It is apparant enough what <hi>Good</hi> the Apoſtle driues at, not euery <hi>good</hi> but the <hi>beſt good;</hi> not the Naturall or Ciuill <hi>good:</hi> (both theſe vaniſh as droſſe in the furnace of affliction:) but the Spirituall, the <hi>Eternall good,</hi> which abides the fiery triall, and as pure
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27779:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> Gold is refined, rather then empai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by it. <hi>All things ſhall worke for their good,</hi> this is, ſhall make for the good of their ſoules, for their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good; ſhall further their <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,</hi> their <hi>Saluation;</hi> ſhal make them more <hi>holy</hi> heere, more <hi>happie</hi> hereafter, more <hi>gracious</hi> on earth, more <hi>glorious</hi> in heauen.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Paradox</hi> which ſoundes harſh, and muſt needs grate the eares of a carnall <hi>Nichodemus,</hi> a conceit moſt abſurd in the iudgement of fleſh and blood, contrary to ſenſe and experience; no meruaile if a <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> will not ſubſcribe to it. Who more baſe, who more contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the eye of the world, then the <hi>Generation of the Iuſt?</hi> No men more miſerable, ſo berounded and enuironed with euilles, that they cannot looke beſide their miſeries: all things conſpire to miſchiefe them. What a ſtraunge aſſertion, beyond all beleefe is this of our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, that <hi>all things worke to their good.</hi> What <hi>all things</hi> (ſayth the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?) what, all <hi>euill?</hi> what, <hi>ſinne?</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:27779:21"/> what, <hi>Affliction?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Immo &amp; pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata.</note> (He that puts the queſtion, aſſoyles it) Yea, <hi>all things.</hi> A large word, of a wide extent, yet not too large. <hi>Generall aſſertions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile little, the whole waight of our comfort, lies in the induction of <hi>Particulars.</hi> Giue mee leaue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to run through <hi>all things,</hi> and to extract this <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation from euery thing.</p>
            <p>For Method-ſake, we will range them into two Heads; either they are <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Euil.</hi> That al <hi>Good things</hi> turne to the <hi>good</hi> of them that are <hi>Good,</hi> will eaſily be granted of all. Briefely then, all <hi>Good,</hi> whether <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme</hi> or <hi>ſubordinate. Supreme</hi> God himſelfe, whether we conſider him in his <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Workes.</hi> For his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, His <hi>Wiſedome</hi> is their <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot,</hi> his <hi>Power</hi> their <hi>Bulwarke,</hi> his <hi>Faithfulneſſe</hi> their <hi>Anchor,</hi> his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence</hi> their <hi>Purueighor.</hi> His <hi>Iuſtice</hi> keepes them from <hi>Preſumption,</hi> his <hi>Mercy</hi> from <hi>Deſpaire.</hi> His <hi>Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> ſerues as a <hi>Bridle,</hi> to curb them from dooing <hi>euill. The Face of the Lord is againſt them that do euill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34, 16.</note> as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27779:22"/> a <hi>Sparre</hi> to encourage them to all good Duties.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>He that ſees in ſecret, will reward them openly.</hi> In a word, they <hi>loue</hi> him for his <hi>goodneſſe, feare</hi> him for his <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> and <hi>imitate</hi> his <hi>Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Workes,</hi> if towardes them in particular, ſometimes hee ſpeakes out of the whirlwind; The <hi>Lyon</hi> roares,<note place="margin">Hoſea 3, 8.</note> then all the Beaſtes of the field tremble. This rough <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> howeuer it perplexe them for a time, yet makes them more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to pleaſe him, more fearfull to offend him. Vſually he ſpeakes to his owne in a gentle ſtill voice,<note place="margin">1 King. 19.12 13.</note> and diſcourſeth with them in a familiar Language: then they <hi>walke</hi> vvith God as <hi>Enoch,</hi> talke with him as <hi>Moſes,</hi> conuerſe with him as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram,</hi> ſupplicate to him, as <hi>Dauid, Ioſuah, Samuel, Danie.</hi> If <hi>towardes Others, generally:</hi> Sometimes hee workes by <hi>meanes;</hi> then his <hi>Glorie</hi> ſhines ſufficiently: they aſcribe the praiſe to him, who both appointed the meanes, &amp; gaue the bleſſing to that meanes he had appointed.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:27779:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Sometimes hee workes <hi>without meanes;</hi> and then his <hi>Glorie</hi> giues a farre greater luſtre:<note place="margin">This is the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God. Exod. 8.19.</note> they crie out <hi>Digitus Dei eſt.</hi> Sometimes he works <hi>aboue, againſt meanes,</hi> then indeede his <hi>Glorie</hi> ſhines out moſt brightly this fils them with wonder and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement, cauſing them to breake out with the Apoſtle: <hi>O the deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the wiſedom &amp; power of God, how vnſearchable are his iudgements and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> Rom. 11, 43. <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> is their <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator,</hi> and <hi>Preſeruer; God</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi> their <hi>Sauiour</hi> and <hi>Redeemer; God</hi> the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> their <hi>Sanctifier</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>God</hi> the ſupreme <hi>Agent,</hi> ſo all <hi>Creatures</hi> in ſubordination to his will, worke for the good of his Choſen, <hi>Whether Men or Angelles.</hi> Lower we may not deſcend, leaſt our diſcourſe know no limits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Angels:</hi> what's their office? are they not ſent forth as <hi>Miniſtring Spirits</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of the elect? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11, 14 In <hi>our</hi> Inſancie, theſe <hi>heauenly peeres</hi> carry vs in their <hi>Armes as Nurſes,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27779:23"/> leaſt we ſhould daſh our feete against a ſtone.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 91, 11, 12</note> In our Nonage, they ſerue as <hi>Tutors or Gouernours,</hi> ſecretly inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating vs to <hi>good,</hi> diſſwading from <hi>euill.</hi> Are we in <hi>priſon?</hi> they can knocke off our Fetters, open the <hi>Brazen gates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 12.7.</note> and ſet vs at liberty to ſhift for our liues. Are we enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with an innumerable <hi>Hoaſt of Armed Enemies?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 19.35</note> they can ſlay a <hi>Hundred and foureſcore &amp; fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> in one night. At our <hi>Death,</hi> they ſtand ready to receiue our flit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſoules, and to carry them into <hi>Abrahams boſome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.22.</note> At the <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> they gather the Bodies of the Saints from the <hi>foure Corners of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Men.)</hi> All <hi>Ordinances</hi> among Men make for them, whether <hi>Ciuil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſticall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 49.23.</note> Ciuill <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are <hi>Nurſing Fathers &amp; nurſing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Church; as the ſhadow of a great rocke to ſhroud them from the rage of the wicked.</hi> Rom. 4.44. <hi>Hee is the Miniſter of God to thee, for Good.</hi> What Good? That we may leade a quiet and peaceable life, <hi>in al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27779:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> and honeſty,</hi> 1 Tim. 2, 2. As <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> ſerue for their Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſo <hi>Miniſters</hi> for their Eternall <hi>Good.</hi> Theſe are <hi>Paſtours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.2.</note> leading them to <hi>greene Paſtures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 52, 7.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe verie feet are Beautifull, becauſe they bring the glad tydings of Saluation. Guides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 1.79.</note> reducing thoſe ſilly <hi>ſheepe,</hi> wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the by-pathes of <hi>Error,</hi> into the way of <hi>peace. Watchmen,</hi> which ſtanding on the Lords watch-To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, keepe Centinel;<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.17.</note> &amp; when they they ſee a plague, giue warning; that being <hi>(praemoniti)</hi> forewarned, they might be <hi>(praemuniti)</hi> fore-ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>The <hi>word of God,</hi> is to them that are ſaued,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.16.</note> the <hi>ſweet ſauour of life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life, the Arme of God to Saluation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1, 16. Pſa. 119.105.</note> 
               <hi>A light vnto their feete, a Lanterne vnto their ſteps;</hi> the <hi>two-edged ſword</hi> of the Spirit, piercing euen to the diuiding aſſunder of the Soule and Spirit, and of the ioynts &amp; marrow. <hi>Heb</hi> 4, 12. That heauenly <hi>Manna,</hi> Diuine <hi>Nectar and Ambroſia</hi> which nouriſheth them vp to Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>Oracles for Direction,</hi> as <hi>apples
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27779:24"/> of Paradiſe, and Flaggons of Wines</hi> for Conſolation: a <hi>Coraſiue</hi> to eate out the proud fleſh; a <hi>Cordiall</hi> to ſtrengthen them in theyr greateſt weakeneſſe. The <hi>Sacraments</hi> are the <hi>Broad Seales</hi> of the great King of Kings, to ratifie and confirme that <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> their <hi>Great Charter,</hi> whereby they lay clayme to that <hi>Immortall inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Outward good things,</hi> whether <hi>Bona Animi, Bona Corporis,</hi> or <hi>Bona Fortunae,</hi> euen theſe become truely <hi>good.</hi> The <hi>gifts of the mind, acutenes of Wit,</hi> is to them as that ſword of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> by whoſe keen edge they are made able to vntie or cut aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Gordian</hi> knots of all Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Dilemmaes.</hi> Depth of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo grounds them in the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, that like Trees which haue taken deepe root, they cannot eaſily be toſſed too and fro with euery blaſt of <hi>Doctrine;</hi> yea the gifts of <hi>Reprobates</hi> aduance the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Elect. Who may ſaue others, but themſelues they cannot ſaue;</hi> like <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs Shipwrights,</hi> that builded an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27779:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> Arke for the ſecuring of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, while themſelues were ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp of the <hi>Deluge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Ornaments of theyr Bodyes.</hi> The beauty of <hi>Eſter</hi> made the whol Church of the <hi>Iewes</hi> fare the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength was <hi>Iſraels</hi> Bulwarke, and the wracke of <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims.</hi> The <hi>Gifts of Fortune</hi> (as wee commonly terme them) are nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly emproued by them. If they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Fauourites to Great men, <hi>Lot Ioſeph, Dauid, Nehemiah, Mordecai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11.10.</note> riſe and climbe. <hi>When the righteous are exalted, the City ſhall flouriſh.</hi> If their Cup ouerflow, their <hi>Breſts bee full of Milke, and their Bones full of Marrow;</hi> there wordly Wealth makes them rich in <hi>good Workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>to doe good, and to diſtribute they forget not.</hi> Now they are <hi>Eies</hi> to the <hi>blind, Clothes</hi> to the <hi>naked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 31, 17, 18 19, 20. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Feete</hi> to the <hi>lame:</hi> their Morſels are neuer eaten alone, the <hi>loines of the poore ſhall bleſſe</hi> them.</p>
            <p>My promiſe was not to dwel on this branch, which requires not <hi>confirmation,</hi> but onely <hi>illuſtration.</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:27779:25"/> Why ſhould I waſte the time, in prouing what none denies? Here's the maine <hi>Scruple,</hi> a <hi>Quaere</hi> not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily aſſoyl'd: <hi>What do all euil things turne to their good?</hi> I, <hi>All euill too,</hi> by accident, whether of <hi>Sin</hi> or <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Sinne;</hi> whether that of our firſt Parents, or what flowes from thence. That of our <hi>firſt Parents?</hi> Our Apoſtacie from God in the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> made way for the <hi>incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Second.</hi> Had wee not fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> wee could neuer haue ſtood in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at the firſt was put into our owne hands; but how eaſily were we beguiled by that wily Serpent (like little Children, that will part with Gold for a Nut-ſhelle) to let goe <hi>God, Heauen,</hi> our <hi>Soules,</hi> and all for an <hi>Apple.</hi> Whereas now, this <hi>Iewell</hi> is kept vnder looke and key, in the Boſome of God, conueighed to vs by our Head Chriſt Ieſus; and as ſoone may Satan pull <hi>Chriſt</hi> their <hi>Head</hi> out of Heauen, as ſnatch a <hi>rib,</hi> a <hi>member,</hi> a <hi>limbe</hi> from his <hi>body.</hi> Loe how we haue gayned by our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27779:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> loſſel: our Happineſſe is enlarged, confirmed, &amp; we may triumphing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude with the <hi>Philoſopher:</hi>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q> 
               <hi>Wee had periſhed, if we had not peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which flowes from our <hi>firſt Parents,</hi> whether <hi>Originall Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>Actuall Tranſgreſsion. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Corruption,</hi> howeuer it ſticke cloſe to all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> as an <hi>Hereditary Leproſie</hi> bred in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> &amp; wil not our of the <hi>bone.</hi> Wel may it bee ſubdued, rooted out it cannot be. If it doe not <hi>Regnare,</hi> it will <hi>Inhabitare.</hi> So hath it fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into our Nature, as the Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie eate into the walles, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſcraped out till the houſe be pulled downe; like that poyſoned <hi>Veſtiment</hi> which the <hi>Poets</hi> faine was giuen to <hi>Hercules,</hi> that would not off till it had torne the skinne from the fleſh, and the fleſh from the bone. This <hi>tainture</hi> ſieges on the <hi>wholeman</hi> in the <hi>vnion</hi> of the <hi>Soule</hi> to the <hi>Body,</hi> and therefore cannot be extirpated, eradicated, till the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27779:26"/> ſeparation of the <hi>Body</hi> from the <hi>Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Fomes Malorum,</hi> workes for their <hi>Good</hi> many waies. It ſerues to humble them; it lets them ſee, that they carry in them the <hi>Spawne</hi> of all <hi>Sinne,</hi> the ſourſe of all <hi>Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> lurkes in their vile Nature; that <hi>by Nature they are Slaues to ſinne, Vaſſals to Satan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Daenen eti pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſquam nati. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Firebrands of Hell, heyres of Condemnation;</hi> that they are naught, ſtarke naught, worſe then naught. Now the firſt ſtep to Chriſtianity, is <hi>Selfe-Deniall</hi> If any man will be <hi>my Diſciple, he muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelfe, and follow me.</hi> If the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition of this <hi>poyſon</hi> and <hi>venom</hi> which lurketh in the Nature of Man, and renders him more odious in the ſight of God then a <hi>Toade, Snake,</hi> or <hi>Serpent</hi> can be hateful to vs, doe not make him out of loue with himſelfe, I know not what will. Certainly, <hi>Paul</hi> was not ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mored with his owne worth, when he cryeth out, <hi>In me</hi> (that is) in my fleſh, <hi>there dwelleth no good thing.</hi> Rom. 7. ver. 18. It driues them to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27779:26"/> Chriſt with lamentable ſighes and groanes; <hi>O miſerable man that I am who ſhall deliuer me from this body of Death? Thankes bee to God thorough Ieſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Rom. 7, 24, 25. verſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe diſeaſed creatures, ſicke as life can hold, how eagerly doe they run vnto the Phyſitian? ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it a moſt ſingular Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if they may with the poore Woman in the Goſpell) but ſteale a touche of the <hi>Hemme</hi> of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours <hi>Garment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 8, 43, 44</note> that ſo this <hi>Iſſue of blood</hi> may bee ſtanched, and this <hi>Spring of Corruption</hi> dryed vppe, which of it ſelfe like a <hi>ſeething pot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 16, 16. Ezech. 24, 6, 7</note> is euer ſending vp a <hi>filthy Scumme,</hi> and like the <hi>raging Sea,</hi> is euer <hi>foa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out myre and dirt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 57, 20, 21</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Actual tranſgreſsions,</hi> the curſed fruit ſprowting from that <hi>roote of Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> whether <hi>Leſſer or Greater,</hi> are made vſefull to the Elect. <hi>Smaller,</hi> in the <hi>Vnderſtanding; Errours</hi> and <hi>doubting,</hi> occaſions them to get a ſurer reſolution, a ſcrupulous mind; (I meane not of ſuch as are more
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27779:27"/> nice then wiſe, which makes doubts where none is, and ſeeke <hi>knots</hi> in a <hi>Bulruſh.</hi>) Like thoſe trees which are ſhaken of the Northerne windes take deeper root and ſtands firmer. The doubting of ſome few, make for the ſatisfaction of many. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſtaggering in that high point of the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> gaue a hint to <hi>Paule,</hi> for the wiping out of all ſcruples both in themſelues and others. No truths more cleare now then thoſe which haue beene here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore moſt <hi>controuerſall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Affections.</hi> Their proane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to anger, wrath, diſſention, Aemulation, ſecret heart-burning, open diſtaſte: Theſe humaine frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties make them more wary, more watchfull.<note place="margin">Acts. 15.39.</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> fall at variance, their diſcord breakes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a rent or ſeparation; this ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion tended much to the ſpreading of the Goſpell. Howſoeuer, theſe ſlips let them ſee their owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, now they know they are but men; now they learne to curbe their exorbitant paſſions, and will not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27779:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> be not ſo fooliſh as to lay the reines on the neckes of thoſe vnruly hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which if they once get head will indanger their owne necke and their Maſters too. I but what ſhall we thinke of the greater euills?</p>
            <p>Groſſe ſinnes howſoeuer they ſeeme to make <hi>Hauocke</hi> of the graces of the Spirit; like a <hi>Thiefe</hi> in the Candle waſting all, or like ſome blazing Comets prodigiouſly por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ruine and deſolation to that Soule which is ſo fouly ouer-taken: yet out of this <hi>Ranke poiſon</hi> the <hi>Grand</hi> Phyſitian fetches a <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Treacle,</hi> vſing the blood of the <hi>Scorpion</hi> to cure the <hi>ſting</hi> of the <hi>Scorpion. This turnes to their owne good, the good of their Brethren.</hi> To their owne <hi>Good</hi> many wayes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them more humble, more meeke, more wiſe, more caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, more wary, and more Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. Theſe foule <hi>Enormities</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they become <hi>Publike ſcandals</hi> to God and Man, are thoſe ſtinging <hi>Coraziues</hi> which eate downe that <hi>Pride of heart, and ſelfe-conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27779:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> to too much ouerweening their owne worth.</hi> A ſinne which though it make little noiſe in the eares of the world, yet appeares farre more odious and abominable in the ſight of God, then thoſe <hi>Carnall fleſhly ſins</hi> which the world cenſures ſo deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as it make them more humble in themſelues,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> ſo it renders them more gentle to their <hi>Brethren. If any man be fallen by occaſion into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fault, reſtore ſuch a one with the Spirit of meekneſſe</hi> is the Iniunction of the Apoſtle. Thoſe <hi>Phiſitians</hi> which neuer felt paine themſelues, handle their weake <hi>Patients</hi> more rigidly and more roughly. God ſuffers ſometimes euen Famous and Eminent Men; <hi>(Starres of the firſt Magnitude)</hi> to fall fearefully <hi>into groſſe ſinnes,</hi> that they might put to their helping hand, to raiſe vp o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more willingly, and inſtruct them more feelingly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it makes them more wiſe and wary. The <hi>Burnt childe</hi> wil dread the fire. No wit ſo good as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27779:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> that which is <hi>deere bought.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euen fooles by ſuffering are made wife: he is a Foole and a Mad-man both, that will ſtumble twice at the ſame ſtone. Theſe <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenta</hi> are to them <hi>Documenta;</hi> If they learne wiſdom by <hi>other mens harmes,</hi> much more by their <hi>Owne.</hi> Such falles and ſhrewd knockes, teach them to looke before them, and euer after to take ſurer footing. As theſe <hi>groſſe eſcapes</hi> tend to their owne <hi>Good,</hi> ſo to the <hi>Good</hi> of their Brethren, for their <hi>Comfort &amp; Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Comfort:</hi> How many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands had beene plunged into the <hi>Gulfe of Deſpaire,</hi> had they not bene vpheld by the miſcarriage of ſome few of the Saints? Haſt thou bene an <hi>Adulterer,</hi> a <hi>Murtherer,</hi> viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Bed</hi> firſt, and then embru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy hands in the <hi>blood</hi> of thy Brother? <hi>Dauid</hi> comes to thee if thou canſt <hi>Beleeue and Repent,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire not: I robbed my loyall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of his wife, of his life, and yet I was reſtored to <hi>the ioy of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51, 12.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:27779:29"/> 
               <hi>I confeſſed my ſin, and the Lord forgaue mine iniquity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 32.5.</note> Haſt thou bin a <hi>griping Extortioner,</hi> a <hi>proling Catch pole;</hi> grinding the faces of the poor, and ſelling the needy for ſhooes? <hi>Zacheus</hi> comes to thee, <hi>Repent, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and diſpaire not,</hi> for I was an <hi>Oppreſsing-Exactor,</hi> an <hi>Exacting Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19.9.</note> yet <hi>Saluation</hi> came vnder my Roofe, and I was made the Childe of <hi>Abram.</hi> Haſt thou bin a <hi>Bloudie Perſecutor,</hi> an horrible Blaſphemer? <hi>Paul</hi> comes to thee, <hi>Repent, Beleeue, diſpaire not,</hi> I worried the tender Lambes of Chriſt (cruell Woolfe and Tyger as I was) &amp; made much hauocke of the Flocke: my foule mouth belched out hideous Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt God and Heauen; yet I found mercy, and became a <hi>Choſen veſſell,</hi> of a <hi>Saul,</hi> a <hi>Paul;</hi> of a <hi>Perſecutor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9.15.</note> a <hi>Preacher of the Name of Chriſt.</hi> Haſt thou beene a ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Caterpillar,</hi> a Robber by the Highway; whoſe whole <hi>Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was a Trade of <hi>vileneſſe</hi> and <hi>vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany;</hi> one that had ſold thy ſelfe to <hi>work wickedneſſe</hi> all the daies of thy
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27779:29"/> life, and now art gaſping out thy laſt breath, thy heart-ſtrings readie to cracke aſſunder, thy <hi>Soule</hi> almoſt torne from thy <hi>Body;</hi> the <hi>Theefe on the Croſſe</hi> cries to thee, <hi>Repent, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and diſpaire not;</hi> I knew no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trade to liue by but <hi>ſtoile</hi> and <hi>rapine;</hi> this I practiſed, til the hand of Iuſtice faſtened my hands and feete to this wood; neither felt I any remorſe for my lewde courſe, till I came to the point of death, yet was I receiued into <hi>Paradiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 23.43.</note>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15, 4.</note> Wherefore are theſe <hi>things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten but for our Inſtruction and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort?</hi> Theſe foule Crimes are recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not in hatred to them, but in Loue to vs.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Caution</hi> ſecondly. Who are we that we ſhould preſume of our owne ſtrength, when wee ſee the weakneſſe of thoſe <hi>Braue Worthies?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12</note> 
               <hi>Let him that ſtandeth take heed leaſt he fall.</hi> If the <hi>tall Caedars of Lebanon</hi> bee thus toſſed, and in a manner torne vp by the rootes; what ſhall become of the <hi>ſhrubs?</hi> If the <hi>pillars</hi> be ſhaken, how ſhall the rafters hold
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27779:30"/> out?</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, how the <hi>euill of ſin,</hi> whether great or ſmall; leſſer or groſſer, workes to the <hi>good of Gods choſen:</hi> no meruaile then, if the <hi>euill of puniſhment,</hi> the conſequence of <hi>ſinne,</hi> haue the ſame effects, whether <hi>Inward or Outward. Inward,</hi> whether <hi>Spirituall</hi> deſertion, or anguiſh of minde. Theſe bee the vnhappy twins of that curſed dam, <hi>Spirituall Deſertion.</hi> A ſad and dolefull condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is, when the Father of lights ſhall withdraw the <hi>Light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4, 6.</note> 
               <hi>which is better</hi> then life it ſelfe; when the <hi>Almighty</hi> ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our enemy, and ſhall ſet vs as a Marke or But to ſhoote at: when this Arrowes ſhall <hi>ſticke faſt in our ribbes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>and the venome thereof ſhall drink vp our blood. When the terrors of God fight againſt vs. When the Lion ſhall teare vs in peeces, and there is none to deliuer vs.</hi> When the Lord ſhall turne the deafe eare to our roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.41.</note> ſighs, and groanes: <hi>We call and cry, but none heareth; yea euen to the Lord, but he anſwereth not.</hi> This for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27779:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> thoſe ſad complaints from the <hi>man after Gods owne heart. Haſt thou forgotten to bee mercifull? Haſt thou ſhut vp thy louing kindneſſe in euerlaſting forgetfulneſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>How long (Lord) how long, wilt thou abſent thy ſelfe for euer?</hi> This made <hi>Iob</hi> a <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> to himſelfe. But, oh the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Good</hi> which redounds from this vnſpeakeable <hi>griefe!</hi> Firſt, this <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> breakes our flinty hearts. <hi>A broken and a contrite ſpririt (O God) thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> None more comfortable, then ſuch as haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through theſe vncomfortable <hi>ſtormes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. Therefore doth he <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> himſelfe for a <hi>moment,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deere his preſence, that wee might greete him with a double welcome, and not too eaſily forgoe what can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obtained, without great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty. The Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> ſuffers her <hi>Beloued to ſtand knocking without doores:</hi> though hee plead his <hi>locke were wet with the droppes of the dew: Open my Loue, my Doue, my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled.</hi> The lazie fit was on her,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27779:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> loth ſhee is to ſtir out of her warme neſt, there he muſt waite and coole his heeles.<note place="margin">Can. 5.2.3.4.</note> No ſooner doth the <hi>Bridegroome</hi> out of a iuſt diſtaſt draw backe, but ſhe comes to her ſelfe, ſees her folly, caſts off her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernes, ſtarts vp, forth of Doores ſhe gets her; ſeeking, enquiring him <hi>whom her ſoul loued,</hi> ſhe purſues him (as it were) with <hi>heu and cry,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues neuer to giue ouer ſeeking (though beaten and buffeted blacke and blew) till ſhee haue found him; and then claſps hands about his necke, and will bee ſure to hold him faſter then her owne life. The other brat and abortiue conception of that vgly monſter, is <hi>anguiſh of minde.</hi> An inſupportable euill. The <hi>ſpirit of a man, can beare all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18.14.</note> but a <hi>wounded ſpirit who can beare?</hi> When Conſcience <hi>writes bitter things againſt vs,</hi> and cauſes vs to <hi>poſſeſſe the ſinnes</hi> of our youth,<note place="margin">Iob. 13.26.</note> 
               <hi>ſetting them in order before vs:</hi> who is able to endure the gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Cheſt-worme? Which is euer corroding our hearts like a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27779:31"/> greedy <hi>Vulture,</hi> and eating through our bowels, like a <hi>curſed viper.</hi> Who can endure the heate of this <hi>Aetna</hi> when it flaſhes the flames of hell fire in our faces? Who can endure the ſtroakes and ſtabbes of this <hi>helliſh fiend,</hi> perſecuting vs (as it dogged <hi>Brutus</hi>) with a drawne Sword, ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing it to the very hilts in our hart? of this <hi>Snaky Alecto</hi> ſtinging vs with a perpetuall <hi>Remorſe.</hi> Euery new ſinne is (as it were) a new <hi>Snake,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery renewed act of ſinne, giues a new ſtab; euery ſtab more mortall then the biting of a <hi>Serpent,</hi> or ſting of an <hi>Adder, Prou.</hi> 23.32. Yet euen thoſe <hi>teares,</hi> are the <hi>foode of Angels;</hi> thoſe <hi>ſighes</hi> ſweet <hi>muſicke</hi> in the eares of God; that <hi>griefe,</hi> the <hi>ioy of heauen.</hi> By this rough tract &amp; thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny path, their feete are guided into the <hi>way of Peace;</hi> thoſe <hi>Agonies</hi> make way for the <hi>Prince of Peace;</hi> who came not to <hi>Call the righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>but ſinners to Repentance. Sinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>that labour and are laden with the weight of their ſinnes;</hi> to them he giues that peace which <hi>paſſeth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 4.7.</note>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:27779:32"/> Both theſe put together, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an Image of Hell. <hi>Spirituall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion,</hi> is that <hi>poena Damni,</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of loſſe. <hi>Anguiſh of minde,</hi> is that <hi>poena ſenſus,</hi> puniſhment of ſenſe; an eſtate little differing from that of the <hi>Damned,</hi> ſaue onely in Degree and Continuance. By theſe <hi>Gates of Hell,</hi> many times the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Saints of God, ſaile <hi>to Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe inward <hi>Euils</hi> which doe pierce thorough our very ſoules, become thus profitable; much more thoſe outward miſeries, which though great enough, in themſelues are but <hi>Flea-bitings</hi> in compariſon of the other. May it pleaſe you to ſee this fulfilled in the <hi>Generals,</hi> in the <hi>Particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Generally,</hi> all outward affliction works to their <hi>good:</hi> whoeuer <hi>plowes</hi> not with the <hi>Heifer of the Spirit, ſhall neuer vnfold this Riddle;</hi> How <hi>meate</hi> comes out of the <hi>Eater; Sweet</hi> out of the <hi>Sowre;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 14, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Hony</hi> out of the <hi>Lyon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Tribulation</hi> brings forth <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; Patience, Experience; Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Hope, that maketh not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:27779:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> The light &amp; momentarie <hi>affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this life,</hi> cauſe to vs a far <hi>more excellent,</hi> an eternal weight of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> This Leſſon the <hi>Holy ones</hi> learne in the Schoole of <hi>Experience,</hi> that howeuer no <hi>affliction</hi> but is gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous for the time, not ioyous;<note place="margin">Hebr. 12, 11.</note> yet after, it brings the <hi>quiet fruit of peace to them that are thereby exerciſed.</hi> They finde more ſolid ioy in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for Chriſt,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11, 25.</note> then in all the <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin, which laſt but for a ſeaſon.</hi> Gods <hi>Sheepe</hi> thriue beſt in <hi>Salt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes,</hi> his <hi>Corne</hi> is pareſt from <hi>Chaffe</hi> when it is vnder the <hi>Flaile:</hi> his <hi>Gold</hi> freeſt from <hi>droſſe</hi> when caſt into the <hi>fiery furnace:</hi> theſe <hi>ſtars</hi> ſhine brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in the darkeſt night: their feete tread ſureſt in the rougheſt way.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prodigall</hi> ſpend-thrift thinks not of <hi>Home</hi> till hee was pinched with <hi>Famine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 15, 17.</note> &amp; brought to a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of bread. <hi>Hagar</hi> was proude and pierke in the houſe of <hi>Abram,</hi> but gentle and tractable in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe. <hi>Ionah</hi> lyes ſnoring and ſnorting in the ſhip; watching and praying in the <hi>Whales</hi> belly. Thoſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27779:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>noble Vines</hi> planted with Gods owne hand, would run wilde, into <hi>Luxuriant</hi> branches, and bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne with many noiſome luſtes, were they not euer and anone pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſome ſanctified trouble. <hi>In their affliction they will ſeeke mee early.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 5.15.</note> While the Sunne-ſhine of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity laſted,</hi> God ſent his <hi>Prophets,</hi> riſing vp early, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe late, ſtretching out their hands and throats al the day long: but theſe <hi>deafe Adders ſtoppe theyr eares at the voice of the Charmer,</hi> till the Aule of <hi>Afflictions</hi> come, then their eares are boared, then they ſeeke them as eagerly, as he ſought him earely. Let mee then for the <hi>Generall</hi> conclude with <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lamen. 3, 27.</note> 
               <hi>It is good for a man to beare the yoake from his youth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71.</note> with <hi>Dauid, It is good for vs that we are afflicted:</hi> with <hi>Paul, All things worke together for the good of them that loue God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Particulars: Priuate, Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Calamities,</hi> make all for the <hi>beſt</hi> too. <hi>Priuate,</hi> whether in their <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> or in their <hi>Name,</hi> or on theyr
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27779:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Perſons.</hi> In their <hi>Eſtate:</hi> Are they pinched with want and penurie?<note place="margin">Dan. 1, 12.</note> fed <hi>with pulſe and water</hi> as <hi>Daniel,</hi> this lets them ſee,<note place="margin">Prou. 15, 16.</note> a <hi>little vvith the feare of the Lord, is better to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, then great riches to the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Howeuer poore in this world, yet they are <hi>rich in God;</hi> and this corporall pouerty, fittes them for the <hi>Kingdome of God.</hi> They haue a Feaſt which the world knows not of. Beſides, whether (I beſeech you) hath better experience of the Loue, Goodneſſe, and Care of his Heauenly Father, he that wallowes in his wealth, and <hi>ſacrifices to his owne Net,</hi> or he who is fedde from hand to mouth as it were from <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> Who will not preferre the courſe fare brought to <hi>Elijas</hi> by thoſe ſtraunge Catorers the <hi>Rauens</hi> before all the dainties which were ſerued vp to <hi>Ababs</hi> Table?<note place="margin">1 Kings 17.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In their <hi>Good Names.</hi> If their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation be blacke with <hi>infamy;</hi> if ſome ſtinking <hi>Fly</hi> be falne into that ſweete <hi>Oyntment,</hi> which makes it putrifie, either this ſtaine is drawne
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27779:34"/> vpon themſelues deſeruedly, or ſome dirt is caſt in their faces by the hand of <hi>Malice</hi> or <hi>Enuy.</hi> What comes through their owne default, they beare it patiently, &amp; improue it profitably Theſe are the thoughts wherewith they entertaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. What? is it ſuch a <hi>hell</hi> to bee in diſgrace with Men, that a man had as good be <hi>halfe hanged, as haue his credit cracke;</hi> oh what a hell is it to be out of fauour with God, to be ſhamed, diſcarded before <hi>Men and Angels at the Generall Aſsiſe</hi> of the whole World! What Malice or Envy caſts vpon them if for a good cauſe,<note place="margin">1 Peter 4.14.</note> they <hi>glory in that ſhame,</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it the greateſt grace in all the world, to ſuffer diſgrace for vvell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</p>
            <p>Euils on their <hi>perſons,</hi> vvhether <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> or <hi>Death.</hi> For <hi>Corporal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities,</hi> God often recompences outward <hi>defects,</hi> with a ſupply of inward <hi>Grace.</hi> If <hi>Naaman</hi> the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian had not beene a Leaper in his body, the Leproſie of his ſoule (I feare) had neuer beene cured. How
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27779:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> many flocking to Chriſt for the cure of their bodies, obtained the ſaluation of their Soules; like <hi>Saul,</hi> who ſeeking for <hi>Aſſes,</hi> ſtumbled on a <hi>Crowne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4, 16.</note> As the <hi>outward man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes, ſo the inward is ſtrengthened.</hi> Could we performe in our health, what we promiſe on our ſicke-bed; wee ſhould liue more like <hi>Angelles</hi> then <hi>Men.</hi> Death it ſelfe, that <hi>King of Terrors</hi> to a natural man;<note place="margin">Iob. 14, 18.</note> as the Philoſopher obſerues, of all <hi>fearfull</hi> things, the moſt <hi>fearefull</hi> to them is but the <hi>Gate to Life.</hi> The <hi>Sting</hi> of this Serpent is pulled out, and they dare lay it in their <hi>boſome.</hi> It vvas firſt threatned as a <hi>Curſe, The ſoule that ſinnes ſhall Dye;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> it is now tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a <hi>Bleſsing.</hi> If wee had our hope in this life onely,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15, 19.</note> 
               <hi>We were of all men the moſt miſerable.</hi> Bleſſed <hi>are they that dye in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>for they reſt from their labours, and theyr Workes follow them.</hi> Their whole life, is a continuall <hi>Combate</hi> with the world, the fleſh, and the diuell: euery day they bring home new <hi>Spoyles,</hi> new <hi>Trophees,</hi> but are neuer crowned til the laſt.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:27779:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Sampſons,</hi> make foule <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocke</hi> of their Enemies: many terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>ſlaughters</hi> and <hi>maſſacres</hi> do the <hi>Philiſtms</hi> ſuffer from their hands, during their life; but the dead which they ſlay at their death,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.30.</note> are farre more then thoſe which were ſlaine in their life. They bow downe with all their might, the pillars of the clay <hi>Cottages</hi> fall, and at once they are auenged of all their <hi>Aduerſaries:</hi> Thus is the day of <hi>Death</hi> better to them,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.3.</note> then the day of their <hi>Birth;</hi> being indeed, the <hi>Doomeſday</hi> of their <hi>miſery,</hi> their <hi>Birth-day</hi> of <hi>Glory.</hi> As for their <hi>Carkaſſes,</hi> which they leaue behinde them, as the <hi>Snake</hi> his skin in the <hi>thicket,</hi> that they might renew their ſtrength as an <hi>Eagle;</hi> are they not committed as <hi>Good ſeede</hi> into the <hi>Granary</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi> there to die that they may bee quickned? Shall not thoſe leaues which fall in this <hi>Autumne,</hi> at the <hi>ſpring</hi> of the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Reſurrection</hi> ſproute forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.42.</note> Sowen <hi>they are in Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but ſhall be raiſed in <hi>Incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> ſowen in <hi>diſhonour,</hi> but ſhall bee
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27779:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> raiſed in <hi>Glory. With theſer very eyes ſhall I ſee my Redeemer;</hi> ſayd,<note place="margin">Iob. 17.26.27.</note> 
               <hi>that Mirror of Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>prîuate</hi> and <hi>perſonall</hi> miſeries; ſo <hi>publicke</hi> and <hi>Nationall Calamities</hi> aduance their <hi>Good.</hi> Put the caſe, ſome <hi>ſtrange iudgement</hi> ouertake a <hi>People</hi> which threatens nothing but <hi>Ruine, Deſolation, Deuaſtation;</hi> a <hi>iudgement,</hi> the very ſound whereof, would make any Mans eares to tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle that heares it; a ſweeping ſtorme, that beares all downe before it; when the Lord (it ſhould ſeeme) intends <hi>To cut roote and branches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>head and taile,</hi> and wipe out their name from <hi>vnder Heauen;</hi> this makes for them many waies. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are <hi>houſed</hi> before the ſtorme. Tender hearted <hi>Ioſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 22.20. 1 King. 14.13. 2 King. 20.19.</note> 
               <hi>good Abijah, vpright Hezekiah;</hi> were they not all <hi>Gathered to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in peace:</hi> and (as the Prophet ſpeaks more generally of the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) taken away from the euill to come.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 57.1.</note> 
               <hi>Sometimes,</hi> they are <hi>ſhrouded</hi> from the ſtorme. <hi>Noah</hi> rides ſafely in a well-pitch'd <hi>Arke,</hi> when the whole
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:27779:36"/> world was couered with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>Deluge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.23.</note> 
               <hi>Lot</hi> eſcapes with his wife,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.21.22.</note> and finds a ſhelter in <hi>Zoar,</hi> when <hi>Sodome and Gommorah</hi> were turned into <hi>Aſh heapes. Sometimes,</hi> they haue a <hi>Calme</hi> in the midſt of the <hi>ſtorme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 10.23.</note> There was light in <hi>Goſhen</hi> when all <hi>Aegypt</hi> was clouded with a thicke and groſſe darkeneſſe. <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fleece</hi> was dry,<note place="margin">Iudg. 6.39.</note> when all the earth was wet. The <hi>Mourners in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 9.6.</note> were ſecured in that <hi>Generall maſſacre.</hi> When <hi>Iſrael</hi> was led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captiuity, then was <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſet at liberty. The Prophet finds more fauour with the Princes of <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 40.4.</note> then from the Peeres of <hi>Iſrael? Sometimes,</hi> (as vſually it fals out) they are enwrapped in the <hi>Common Calamities;</hi> yet that is in mercy to them, which to others becomes a iudgement.</p>
            <p>For firſt, <hi>God</hi> euer <hi>threatens</hi> before he <hi>ſtrikes.</hi> The <hi>ſtorme</hi> hanges and houers a long time ouer their heads, ere it fal. The <hi>meſſengers of God</hi> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon them to <hi>Repentance;</hi> lay open there ſins, denounce <hi>iudgement.</hi> As
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:27779:36"/> 
               <hi>Ionah to Nineueh; yet forty dayes and Niniueh ſhall bee deſtroyed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ionah. 3.4.</note> Theſe <hi>peales</hi> ſounded in their eares; thoſe <hi>viſions</hi> preſented to their eyes; rouze them from the <hi>deepe ſleepe</hi> of <hi>Security;</hi> and now how doe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirre themſelues; conſidering their wayes, ranſacking their hearts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing their ſinnes; <hi>Preparing to meete their God, with Aſhes on their heades, Sackcloth on their backs, Feares in their eyes, Sorrow in their hearts, Prayers in their lips, and ropes in their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, admit the <hi>Sentence</hi> bee irreuocable, the <hi>Iudge</hi> be inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, his <hi>wrath</hi> vnplacable: they haue ioyn'd in the ſinnes, and therefore muſt ſhare in the <hi>plagues of their Nation:</hi> euen this is in fauour: they are but corrected heere, that they might not bee condemned heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Theſe plagues may kill them, but cannot hurt them; they may <hi>rent the garments of their bodies,</hi> but their ſoule is invulnerable; they do but ſhorten their miſery, and haſten their <hi>Glory.</hi> Yea, euen that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:27779:37"/> 
               <hi>Spirituall iudgement,</hi> which of all others is moſt fearefull; makes to their aduantage.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Golden Candleſticke</hi> bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued from one <hi>Nation,</hi> is it not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to <hi>another?</hi> The <hi>Goſpell</hi> (like the Sea) it looſeth ground in one place, getteth footing <hi>elſwhere.</hi> If the <hi>Sun ſet</hi> to one <hi>Horizon,</hi> it ariſeth to <hi>another.</hi> The <hi>falling of the Iewes,</hi> was the <hi>riſing of the Gentiles:</hi> when they were caſt off with a <hi>Lo-ruhamah,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Lo-anni;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 1.8.9.</note> to vs that <hi>were not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God,</hi> was it ſaid, <hi>Yea are the Sons of the liuing God.</hi> When the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the <hi>Euening</hi> were ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ouer <hi>Aſia,</hi> the day dawned to vs in <hi>Europe.</hi> If our <hi>vnworthineſſe</hi> ſhould depriue vs of this <hi>light, (Quod omen Deus Auertat</hi>) it would doubtſly bee giuen to a <hi>Nation</hi> that ſhall bring foorth <hi>better fruits, ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the glorious Goſpell of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> with their holy and Chriſtian Conuerſation, which wee haue ſoulely blemiſhed with our horrible and hainous <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:27779:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Thus you ſee, what a rich <hi>Mine of Conſolation</hi> is heere conueighed vnto vs; a <hi>Mine</hi> that cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted. The <hi>Well</hi> is deepe, the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per we go ſtill the ſweeter it is: It is not the weake Backet of our <hi>ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Capacity,</hi> though let downe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo often, that can dreine this <hi>Spring.</hi> Much water haue we drawn vp already, and perhaps the Reader may thinke too much, yet nothing in compariſon of what is left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde. What is a <hi>drop</hi> to the <hi>Ocean?</hi> May I not ſafely and boldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude now, <hi>All thinges, all Good, God, Angels, Men, the ordinances of men; Ciuill, Eccleſiaſticall; gift of body, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of the minde, and eſtate. All e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, of ſinne, Originall, Actuall; ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, groſſer; of punniſhment, inward, ſpirituall, diſertion, horror of minde: outward, priuate miſeries on their goods, good name, or perſons: publike calamities: temporall, ſpirituall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> all <hi>worke</hi> for the <hi>beſt</hi> of thoſe that <hi>loue God.</hi> Ere I proceed to the application of the point, I muſt cleare the way by <hi>remouing ſome
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:27779:38"/> ſcruples,</hi> which otherwiſe will lye as ſo many <hi>rubs</hi> to <hi>blocke</hi> vp our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
            <p>How does all euill worke for the Good of <hi>Gods choſen,</hi> when euen <hi>Good things proue ſometimes ſnares to the Righteous?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 30, 6.7.</note> Was not the <hi>man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods owne heart, puffed vp with his proſperity: I ſaid I ſhall neuer be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi> Was not <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſicke of the ſame <hi>diſeaſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 10.15.17.</note> who tooke ſo deepe a <hi>ſurfet</hi> of <hi>plenty,</hi> that the Prophet was forced to miniſter a ſharpe <hi>purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> To this I anſwere. For, the moſt part, as the Lord conferres his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours vpon them; ſo hee giues them <hi>Grace</hi> to make a right vſe of them: as he wrings to them <hi>waters out of a full Cup,</hi> ſo hee giues them a <hi>ſteady hand</hi> to carry this <hi>Cup</hi> without ſpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.10.</note> If they be hedged in with bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings as ſometimes <hi>Iob,</hi> this hedge ſerues as awal of braſſe, wherby the ſuggeſtions of Sathan are <hi>Baracca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doed</hi> out. If at any time the tempter ſollicites to any vnlawful ſuites, they retort that of <hi>Ioſeph:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhall I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this great euill and ſinne againſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:27779:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> God,</hi> that God who hath <hi>laden mee with his</hi> bleſſing, whoſe mercies are <hi>renewed vpon mee euery morning,</hi> and euery moment If at any time they are left to themſelues, it is but for <hi>probation, for humiliation;</hi> to let them ſee their owne <hi>weakeneſſe, the worlds vanity, Gods goodneſſe. Their owne weakeneſſe,</hi> to leane with the whole weight and ſtreſſe of their bodies, vpon thoſe <hi>broken reeds</hi> and hollow Canes of <hi>Aegypt. The worlds vanity;</hi> which (as the Wiſeman ſpeakes of riches) <hi>taketh to herſelfe the wings of an Eagle:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15, 5.</note> If ſhee ſtoope not to vs, we cannot catch her, if ſhe <hi>ierke</hi> from vs, wee cannot hold her. No glaſſe ſo brittle as the <hi>glaſſy Sea of this world. Gods goodneſſe;</hi> that held them vp ſo long from falling, that kept them from periſhing in the fall.</p>
            <p>But this is not my condition, will ſome weake ſoule pretend; I am no whit bettered by my <hi>Croſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scruples of minde.</note> or <hi>Comforts;</hi> I find my heart too much <hi>elated</hi> in my proſperity; too much <hi>deiected</hi> in aduerſity; I am neuer wel
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27779:39"/> 
               <hi>full nor faſting.</hi> Let the <hi>Sunne ſhine,</hi> who more <hi>briske?</hi> Let it be ecclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, my iniurious diffidence and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of <hi>Gods prouidence,</hi> ſecret mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, and open repinings, get ground vpon me, and like ill weeds grow ſo faſt, that I feare mee, the <hi>ſeede of Grace</hi> is (in a manner) choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſtifled.</p>
            <p>Alas, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> ſilly Soule; Iudge not thy ſelfe according to <hi>appearance</hi> while the fits laſts. The <hi>miſt of temptations</hi> haue now clouded thy ſoule; <hi>A blind man is not fit to iudge of colours.</hi> The <hi>water</hi> is now trobled, the <hi>mud</hi> raiſed, it is impoſſible to ſee cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The <hi>Phyſick</hi> may happily work churliſhly, and for a Fit trouble the <hi>Patient</hi> more then the diſeaſe it ſelf. Tell mee, doeſt thou not bewayle thy diffidence, impatience? Doeſt thou not ſtriue and ſtruggle againſt them with <hi>might</hi> and <hi>maine?</hi> Be of good comfort; we are not to deale with a rigid <hi>Maſter,</hi> but with a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Father,</hi> that interprets the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> for the <hi>deede;</hi> and accepts of the <hi>will</hi> for the <hi>worke.</hi> Striue <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:27779:39"/> waite <hi>patiently,</hi> thou ſhalt ſee and feele, that as all other croſſes; ſo this (which of all other thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemeſt to bee the greateſt croſſe) ſhall <hi>worke for thy Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto wee haue ſatisfyed the Scruples of weake Chriſtians: now we are to grapple with a peruerſe <hi>generation.</hi> If all things, all euill; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection </seg>2</label> yea, euill of <hi>ſinne:</hi> if all <hi>ſinne</hi> worke for the <hi>beſt</hi> of them that <hi>Loue God:</hi> What doe I thwarting my <hi>Corrupt Naiure?</hi> What do I ſtriuing againſt the ſtreame? Why ſhould I curbe and checke my vnbrideled Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite? Heereafter, I will let looſe the reines to all licentiouſnes; hereafter I will <hi>Gratifie</hi> the fleſh, and humor it in all things: now may I follow the ſwing of my licentious deſires, now may I <hi>ſinne, that Grace may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound;</hi> all will make for <hi>my Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle checkes this male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part miſconſtruction, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> with a ſtrange deteſtation. <hi>What? Shall I doe euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>that good may come thereof? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid.</hi> If any ſuch <hi>helliſh Suggeſtions</hi> be raiſed in our hearts; ſnib them,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27779:40"/> O ſnib them, with a <hi>Get thee behind me Satan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16.23.</note> 
               <hi>for thou vnderstandest not the things of God.</hi> Wilt thou ſurfet thy Body,<note place="margin">Quae Dei ſunt non ſapis.</note> that the Phyſitian may <hi>purge</hi> it? Wilt thou quaffe off a cup of ranke <hi>Poyſon,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi> is at hand? Wilt thou breake thy <hi>head,</hi> that the <hi>Surgeon</hi> may clap on a <hi>Plaiſter?</hi> Wilt thou ſheath thy ſword in thine owne fleſh, <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banke</hi>-like, becauſe there is a <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> wil heale vp the wound? Some broken legges and armes, by a ſtiffe and hard <hi>Callus,</hi> are made ſtronger then they were before; wilt thou wilfully thruſt thy legge or ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out of ioynt, expecting the like ſucceſſe? What is, if this be not, to <hi>Tempt the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 4.</note> 
               <hi>and to turn his grace into wantonneſſe?</hi> Nay rather, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (O man)</hi> how the <hi>glorious Goſpel</hi> of God will bee <hi>ſtained,</hi> the Spirit of God <hi>greeued,</hi> the euill Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>ſolaced,</hi> the weak <hi>diſcouraged,</hi> the wicked <hi>emboldned,</hi> thy Religion <hi>queſtioned,</hi> and thy Saluation <hi>hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> If this will not fright thee; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,</hi> hee that hath promiſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:27779:40"/> 
               <hi>mercy to the penitent,</hi> hath not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>Repentance to the obſtinate. Repentance</hi> is not at thy becke or whiſtle; thou mayeſt as well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>Winde</hi> to blow, the <hi>Sun</hi> to ſhine, as conuert thine owne heart. <hi>Remember,</hi> that true and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned <hi>repentance</hi> may ſecure vs from eternall torments, but cannot alwayes ſecure vs from Temporall Chaſtiſements. In theſe Caſes, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsa culpa retinetur poena;</hi> howeuer God may forgiue the <hi>ſinne,</hi> the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment he will not forgiue. Dauids</hi> fault was remitted, yet hee ſmarts ſoundly for his folly;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.13 14.</note> his <hi>ſweet meat</hi> had <hi>ſowre ſawce.</hi> By that time thou haſt beene as well ſcourged as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> as well ſcorched as <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou wilt take heede of committing the like error, or thruſting thy finger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame fire.</p>
            <p>Now the Coaſt is cleered, all obſtacles remoued, Obiections an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, what ſhould let vs from deſcending to <hi>Application?</hi> This <hi>fountaine branches</hi> it ſelfe into three ſtreames, and yeeldes matter of
<list>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:27779:41"/>
                  <item>Inſtruction.</item>
                  <item>Conſolation.</item>
                  <item>Exhortation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It miniſters <hi>Inſtruction</hi> to the <hi>Godly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſtruction.</note> to the <hi>Wicked. Hearken vnto me yee that feare the Lord.</hi> Beholde here an infallible ground, to euince the certainty of your Saluation. If all things aduance your <hi>Good,</hi> what can impeach it? What blocke can lye in your roade to Heauen? The greateſt <hi>rub</hi> is <hi>Sinne. Sin</hi> (indeede) is that <hi>Wall of partition,</hi> that ſeparats betweene vs, and our God. It is <hi>Sinne</hi> that hindereth good thinges from vs.<note place="margin">Eſay 55, 2. Ier. 5.25. Luke 16.26.</note> 
               <hi>Sin,</hi> is that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>vaſte gulfe,</hi> which intercepts the free and familiar entercourſe of his fauours, and our prayers; the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall exchange or commutation whereof, are the onely <hi>Nerues</hi> and <hi>Sinewes,</hi> that hold life and ſoule to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But if <hi>ſinne</hi> it ſelfe, whither <hi>Great</hi> or <hi>Small,</hi> further <hi>theyr Good,</hi> what can hinder it?</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>Viperous generation</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſprung vp; an Egge of that <hi>Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrice Pelagius,</hi> (being as we ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:27779:41"/> long ſince chilled) is newly hatched, new warmth and life put into it, inſomuch that it hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken forth into a <hi>flying Serpent.</hi> It's ſtrange and admirable to conſider; how many <hi>Learned Rabbins,</hi> (no ſmall <hi>Clerkes,</hi> wiſe enough, if not too wiſe in their owne conceites) bend their wits, buſie their braines to ſtagger the Saints, and to beate them from their <hi>Hold;</hi> contending <hi>tanquam pro Aris &amp; focis,</hi> that,<note place="margin">As for a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life and death.</note> 
               <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more ſure, then that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſure of our Saluation.</hi> What elſe meane thoſe large Volumes, touching the <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> of the <hi>Saints (De Apoſtaſia Sanctorum.)</hi> As if a man might be this day an <hi>Heyre of Heauen,</hi> the next a <hi>firebrand of Hell:</hi> This houre a member of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the next, a limbe of <hi>Satan;</hi> to Day, a <hi>Saint;</hi> to morrow, a <hi>Deuill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See how they are infatuated in the <hi>Fore-front</hi> of their booke,<note place="margin">In ipſo lamine impingere.</note> thus to contradict themſelues. The very Title ouerthrowes the Tractate. What? The <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of <hi>Saints:</hi> If they bee <hi>Saints,</hi> how can they then
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:27779:42"/> be <hi>Apoſtatates?</hi> If they bee <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates,</hi> how can they bee <hi>Saints?</hi> What is, if this bee not, <hi>Vno ore fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidum &amp; calidum ſpirare; To blow hot and cold at a breath.</hi> Surely, ſurely, if once a <hi>true Saint,</hi> that man can neuer be a total <hi>Apoſtatate;</hi> if once a <hi>totall Apoſtatate,</hi> that man was <hi>neuer a true Saint.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Incorruptible.</note> Theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>They went out from vs, but they were not of vs; for if they had beene of vs, they would haue continued with vs.</hi> 1. Iohn, 2.19. The beloued Diſciple ſure was not infected with the <hi>Sowre leauen, Arminaniſme,</hi> his phraſe then muſt haue beene inuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. They <hi>were</hi> ſometimes ours, but now they are not; <hi>for</hi> they are gone from vs;<note place="margin">They were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ours but in ſhew onely.</note> nay (faith <hi>Iohn) they were not of vs;</hi> intimating once their's, and euer their's; once a Saint, and euer a Saint. Certainely theſe great Clerkes <hi>erre not, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, nor the power of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.26.</note> or elſe they forget themſelues exceedingly, while they <hi>ſwim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the ſtreame</hi> of Sacred writ; which ſpeakes in another Dialect,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:27779:42"/> 
               <hi>That the gift and calling of God are without Repentance.</hi> Whereupon,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> the Apoſtle giues the Epithite: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>That whom God loues once, hee loues for euer.</hi> That,<note place="margin">Ier. 32.36.40. Mal. 3.6. Iames. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>in him there is no ſhaddow of change.</hi> That, Chriſt hath prayed (and was heard in that hee prayed for:) that <hi>their Faith faile not. Simon, Simon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 17.9.15.20.</note> 
               <hi>Satan hath deſired to winnow thee, but I haue prayed that thy faith faile not.</hi> Their faith may <hi>faint,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 22.31.32.</note> but <hi>faile</hi> it cannot. They may haue their <hi>ſwooning</hi> fits, &amp; terrible <hi>Agonies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 10.20.</note> but ſtill (as <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Eutichus) their life is in them. Whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not, for his ſeed remaineth in him: neither can he ſinne, becauſe he is borne of God.</hi> 1. Iohn. 3.9. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>ſinne</hi> the ſinne <hi>vnto death.</hi> I know they may fall <hi>fearefully,</hi> as <hi>Dauid,</hi> they may fall <hi>frequently,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou, 24.10.</note> as <hi>Peter. The Righteous man falls ſeuen times a day.</hi> (I ſee no ground why it may not bee intended as well of their falling into <hi>Sinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marke the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> 
               <hi>as into Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction:</hi>) but totally, finally, they cannot fall.<note place="margin">Prou. 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>The Righteous man is an
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:27779:43"/> euerlaſting foundation.</hi> Be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied yee <hi>Select veſſels</hi> with theſe <hi>Bugge-beares;</hi> but go on boldly, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, and in <hi>ſpight</hi> of all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, maugre the malice of Satan, and all his inſtruments, hang out the Apoſtles <hi>flagge of defiance,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the cloze of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt: &amp;</hi> verſe 35. <hi>Be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other Creature, ſhall bee able to ſeparate vs from the Loue of God which is Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Inſtruction.</note>Secondly, as <hi>Iron</hi> ſharpneth <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron;</hi> as the Sunne is ſeene beſt by his owne light; ſo Scripture inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets Scripture, and this place giues light to many other places. Many <hi>excellent promiſes</hi> are made to the <hi>Righteous,</hi> concerning bleſſings, <hi>Temporall;</hi> that in times of famine <hi>they ſhall haue enough;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 5.20. Pſal. 34.10.</note> that, <hi>though Thouſands fall on their right hand, Ten thouſands on their left,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 91.5.6.7</note> 
               <hi>the plague
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:27779:43"/> ſhall not touch them:</hi> and yet <hi>Iobs</hi> penary is gone into a Prouerb.<note place="margin">As poore as Iob.</note> 
               <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> was glad to beg crums, and yet was ſtarued to death: It is ſaid,<note place="margin">Luke. 16.21.22.</note> they that feare the Lord <hi>ſhall want nothing,</hi> when as he that was <hi>Lord of all had nothing:</hi> not ſo much as a houſe to harbor him, or a pillow to reſt his head on.<note place="margin">Mat. 8.20.</note> We ſee by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience how <hi>they</hi> are plagued and die like other men. The limitation is heere expreſſed, which is onely there intimated. The <hi>Sword</hi> ſhal not raze their skinne, nor <hi>pouerty</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach vpon their eſtates; the <hi>Peſt</hi> ſhall not poiſon their bodies if it be for their <hi>Good,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in pregnant termes;<note place="margin">Pſal. 34, 10.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall want nothing that is good for them.</hi> If it be <hi>good</hi> for them to bee kept low in their fortunes, to haue their bodies pinched, and their mindes preplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they ſhall not want that neither. <hi>If good things may proue their bane, they ſhall not haue them; if euill things may do them good they ſhal not want them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto wee haue ſpoken to a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:27779:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> people, whoſe eares are boared; now wee muſt charme the <hi>Deafe Adder.</hi> As this Doctrine ſerues to informe the <hi>Godly,</hi> ſo to inſtructe, and withall to affright the <hi>Wicked,</hi> whoſe curſed Machinations are layde as deepe as hell to <hi>Ruine the Good Man.</hi> Vaine, <hi>Men,</hi> why doe you goe about to miſchiefe those, whome the <hi>Almighty</hi> purpoſes to aduance? Hath the <hi>Lord of Hoastes</hi> engaged <hi>his Honour,</hi> and plighted <hi>his Faith,</hi> that <hi>All things ſhall worke for their Good,</hi> and will yee ſeeke their <hi>Hurt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10, 22 Acts 5.39.</note> Tell me, are ye <hi>ſtronger then God? Will ye be euer fighters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God?</hi> Shal the potſheard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with his <hi>Maker?</hi> Is there any poſſibility of croſſing his deſignes? Is there any <hi>Knowledge, Councell, or Vnderſtanding againſt the LORD?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21.30.</note> Will you euer bee ſnatching at the Signet of his right hand? Will yee euer be raking <hi>in the Apple of his eie? Be wiſe now therefore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zechar. 2, 8.</note> 
               <hi>O ye Kings and Learned, yee that are Princes of the earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Touch not his Annointed, and doe his Prophets no harme.</hi> Pſal.2, 10
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:27779:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>He will rebuke Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15.</note> 
               <hi>and ouer-turne Kingdomes</hi> for their ſakes. Hee will tranſlate <hi>Crownes,</hi> from <hi>Aegypt</hi> to <hi>Aſhur,</hi> from the <hi>Caldees</hi> to the <hi>Medes,</hi> from the <hi>Medes</hi> to the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians;</hi> for the good of his Church. Well may you vexe his <hi>Choſen</hi> for a time, but hurt them you cannot. Well may the Lord vſe you as <hi>Scul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions,</hi> to ſcoure theſe <hi>Veſſels of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> when the ruſt is eaten in too farre; or as <hi>Roddes to ſcourge</hi> his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruely Children. <hi>Aſhur is the rod of mine Anger, and the ſtaffe of mine Indignation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 10, 5.12</note> 
               <hi>I will ſend him vnto a diſſembling Nation,</hi> Eſay 10, 5, 12. But when the ruſt is ſcowred off, the <hi>Scullion</hi> ſhall haue his paiment. When the Childe is corrected, the <hi>Rod</hi> ſhall be caſt into the fire.<note place="margin">Pſalme 14.4. Pſalme 79.3.</note> 
               <hi>O Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, ye that forget God; that deuoure his people as it were Bread, and ſhedde their blood as water in the ſtreetes: He that ſits aboue will ſpeake to you in his wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>and vexe you in his diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You doe but rowle a great ſtone vpon a ſteepe Rocke, which will
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:27779:45"/> tumble back vpon your own heads and grinde all vnder it to powder. <hi>Woe to them that offend any of theſe little ones, it were better that a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were hanged about theyr neckes, and that they were caſt into the Sea.</hi> Math. 18, 6. Would to God, that <hi>Romiſh Strumpet,</hi> that hath <hi>dyed her Garments in the redde blood of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 17, 4, 6.</note> would but take this to hart, and conſider, whateuer Maſſacres, and Treacheries ſhe intends for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,<note place="margin">Gen. 50.20.</note> ſhall be turned (as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to his Brethren, concerning their malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proiects againſt his perſon) to <hi>their Good;</hi> I perſwade my ſelfe, out of very <hi>malice,</hi> ſhee would ceaſe to be <hi>malicious,</hi> and out of very ſpight ſhee would ceaſe to bee ſpightfull: ſhee would intend them no <hi>Euill,</hi> that ſhe might do them no <hi>Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The maine vſe of all is for <hi>Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> Is the beſt ſtill working for vs till we get <hi>Heauen?</hi> What-euer changes or chances befall vs; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we be tumbled and toſſed too and fro as a Leafe ſhaken with the winde, or as the ſtubble ſcattered
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:27779:45"/> before the Whirle-winde. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we may bee counted the <hi>Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4, 13,</note> 
               <hi>the ſcumme of the earth,</hi> heere is our comfort, this hard meaſure laſtes but for a ſhort ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Wee are now labouring vnder the <hi>Bricke-killes in</hi> Aegypt;<note place="margin">Deut. 32.10.</note> wee are now trauailing thorow a vaſt and <hi>Roaring Wilderneſſe:</hi> no meruayle, if we be ſtung with <hi>Fiery Serpents.</hi> Euery day will bee better then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; euery day we approach nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer <hi>Canaan</hi> then other. Our light may bee ecclipſed for a time, the <hi>Sunne</hi> will breake foorth. <hi>Light is ſowen for the righteous, and ioy for the vpright of heart,</hi> Pſalme 97, 11. He that leades vs into <hi>Temptation,</hi> wil not ſuffer vs to be foyled in our <hi>Temptations.</hi> Our croſſes are <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,</hi> our fleſh <hi>mortified,</hi> ſinne <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued,</hi> Grace <hi>encreaſed,</hi> our Glorie ſhall be <hi>perfected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere is our Comfort, in all our croſſes, loſſes; in all troubles and tryals; in all our dangers and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:27779:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> we are ſure to <hi>come off faire,</hi> and gaine by the <hi>Bargaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.13.</note> But it ſhall not bee ſo with the vngodly, they waxe worſe and worſe; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing, and being deceyued. It is a ſure rule in the Schooles, <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria iuxta ſe poſita magis Eluceſcunt;</hi> Contraries mutually oppoſed, lend a luſtre each to other: I hope ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it will not be altogether <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor much beſide our <hi>marke,</hi> to ſhew you briefely and diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that as all things turne vnto the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Good;</hi> ſo all things work the <hi>bane</hi> of the <hi>Bad.</hi> As all things further the <hi>Saluation</hi> of the <hi>one;</hi> ſo all things helpe forward the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> of the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The one, like the <hi>Bee,</hi> ſucke good out of euill, draw <hi>Hony</hi> out of the <hi>ſowreſt Herbe:</hi> The other, like the <hi>Spider,</hi> ſucke venom from the <hi>ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Flower,</hi> and turne good into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.15.</note> Nothing ſo <hi>Good</hi> which they corrupt not, nothing ſo <hi>Holy</hi> which they defile not. <hi>God,</hi> he is the <hi>chiefe Good,</hi> yet his <hi>Mercy</hi> makes them <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume;</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:27779:46"/> his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> driues them to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre;</hi> his <hi>Grace</hi> they turne into <hi>Wantonneſſe,</hi> his <hi>Patience</hi> encreaſes their ſinne, and doubles their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, while they treaſure vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues, <hi>Wrath against the day of Wrath,</hi> Rom. 2. verſe 5. They feare him <hi>ſlauiſhly</hi> for his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and <hi>hate him</hi> vnfeignedly for his Goodneſſe. If <hi>God the Father,</hi> offer himſelfe as a <hi>Creator,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt him: If <hi>God the Sonne,</hi> offer himſelfe as a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> they <hi>Crucifie the Lord of Glory</hi> (to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) <hi>dayly.</hi> Heb. 6. verſe 6. <hi>If God the holy Ghoſt,</hi> offer himſelfe as a <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> they reſiſt deſpight the <hi>Spirit of Grace.</hi> Hebrew. 10. verſe 29.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Angels</hi> are vexed with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding their abominations. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> ſerue for their Terror: If <hi>thou do ill, feare;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>for he beareth not the Sword for naught;</hi> it is either to curb thee, or to cut thee off. <hi>Ministers</hi> are euer raking in their ſores, &amp; rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing their gall'd <hi>backs,</hi> which makes
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:27779:47"/> them kicke and winche, ſtorme and fume like <hi>Mad men.</hi> What enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement can they looke for, but that <hi>Salutation</hi> with which <hi>Ahab</hi> welcommed the Prophet, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> chap. 22. verſe 8.<note place="margin">1 King 22.8.</note> 
               <hi>I hate this man, becauſe he neuer ſpeakes good vnto me, but euill.</hi> Or, as the Deuils gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our Sauiour, <hi>Marke</hi> 1. verſe 24. <hi>Art thou come to torment vs before our time?</hi> The Word of God, is vnto them the <hi>Sauour of Death vnto Death:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.16.</note> this Light is as <hi>the ſhadow of death,</hi> their ſore eyes cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the glaring of the Sunne. The beating of thoſe radiant beames on <hi>Ionahs</hi> head,<note place="margin">Ionah. 4.8.</note> neuer vexed him halfe ſo much, as thoſe heauenly Rayes which a edarted from the <hi>Sunne of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> torments their <hi>harts.</hi> You cannot deuiſe a greater plague then to let them fry in that flame. So it fares with <hi>temporal good things.</hi> Their Honour prooues but like the <hi>Stoole of Eli,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.18.</note> as a ſteepe <hi>Pinacle,</hi> from whence they breake their neckes.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:27779:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Make <hi>Saul</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> he will proue a <hi>Tyrant:</hi> make <hi>Balaam</hi> a Prophet, he will proue a <hi>Wizard, a Sorcerer:</hi> make <hi>Iudas</hi> an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> he wil proue a <hi>Traitor,</hi> a <hi>Deuill.</hi> Their <hi>ſtrength</hi> is peruerted, and giues them an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage beyond their Neighbours, to powre in <hi>ſtrong drinke,</hi> to follow after <hi>ſtrange fleſh,</hi> and to ſhew them ſelues the <hi>Diuels Nazarites,</hi> ſtrong to <hi>ſhedde innocent bloud.</hi> Their <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> is ſet foorth as traps and ſnares to catch fooles: By this <hi>Beagle</hi> they hunt for the <hi>precious Soule</hi> of a man.<note place="margin">Prou. 6.26.</note> Their fauour with <hi>Great men,</hi> is as a <hi>Sword</hi> put into a mad mans hand, whereby they wound themſelues, him that gaue it him, and all that comes neere them. If thoſe <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> get on Horſe-backe, they take a pride to ſee their Maſters <hi>Lacquey</hi> it on foot.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Haman</hi> bee promoted,<note place="margin">Eſter. 3.8.9.</note> the Iewes muſt be cruſhed, <hi>Eſter</hi> 3. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes 8, 9. Let <hi>Doeg</hi> inſinuate into <hi>Saul, Abimelech</hi> with his Brethren, ſhall ſoone be cut off, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22, 9,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.9.</note>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:27779:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> Their Wealth makes them as chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh as <hi>Nabal,</hi> as cruell as <hi>Diues,</hi> not a crumme can bee ſpared for <hi>Lazarus.</hi> As ſottiſh as <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> and <hi>Haman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter. 3.15.</note> who fate ſurfetting and quaffing in the Pallace of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan,</hi> when the <hi>Iſrael of GOD</hi> were weeping &amp; mourning in the Cittie, <hi>Eſter</hi> 3, verſe 15. Their <hi>Wit</hi> makes them geering <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing <hi>Iulianiſtes;</hi> They vvill rather looſe their <hi>Friend,</hi> nay their <hi>Soule,</hi> nay their <hi>God,</hi> then their <hi>Ieſt:</hi> and (if all Trades fayle) they can liue by their <hi>Wits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus all <hi>Good things</hi> become euil to them, much more all <hi>Euill.</hi> The ſinne of their firſt <hi>Parents</hi> is ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their ſcore. <hi>Originall Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſtrippes them of all Grace and Goodneſſe; renders them <hi>Slaues</hi> to <hi>Sinne,</hi> Vaſſalles to <hi>Satan,</hi> bindes them (as it were) in chaines to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leſſer ſinnes,</hi> make way for <hi>Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Groſſe ſinnes</hi> make them pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Scandals,</hi> odious to God and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:27779:48"/> man, ten-fold more the Children of the Diuell. Thereby their harts become <hi>hardned, cruſted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim, 4, 2.</note> theyr <hi>Conſciences ſeared as with hot Irons,</hi> and themſelues <hi>ſtigmatized</hi> with that <hi>Brand</hi> of <hi>Caine,</hi> and of <hi>Iudas,</hi> being left Reprobate to euery <hi>good Worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for euill of <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> Let God forſake them with <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28, 6, 7.8.</note> 1 <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> 28. verſes 6, 7, 8. they will forſake God, and runne from his preſence like <hi>Cain,</hi> turne <hi>Vagabonds. Geneſis</hi> 4. verſe 16.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.16.</note> If the <hi>Euill of Sinne</hi> purſue them, and their owne Conſcience haue rayſed a <hi>Heu and Cry</hi> againſt them, with <hi>Achitophell</hi> they flye to a <hi>Halter</hi> for <hi>Remedie,</hi> and for feare of <hi>Hell,</hi> leape into <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Outward Croſſes</hi> do them no <hi>good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 1.5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. verſes 5, 7. <hi>I haue ſmitten them, yet they haue not turned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me,</hi> is an olde Complaint; nay, much hurt. <hi>Ahaz</hi> in his Affliction <hi>tranſgreſſeth more and more,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28, 22. The wicked King cries out,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:27779:49"/> 
               <hi>This euill comes from the Lord, ſhall I ſerue him any longer?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings. 9, 33.</note> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> chap. 6. verſe 33. <hi>Iobs</hi> Wife, will <hi>Curſe God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>and Dye.</hi> Iob 2. 9.</p>
            <p>Is their <hi>Credite crackt?</hi> They grow as ſhameleſſe now, as they were graceleſſe before; proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their ſinnes (as <hi>Sodome</hi>) and fearing neyther <hi>God, nor Man?</hi> Is their <hi>ſtate impoueriſhed?</hi> The ſtick not to put foorth their handes to vnlawfull ſhiftes, adding <hi>Sin</hi> to <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</hi> In the <hi>Diſeaſes of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> with <hi>Aſa,</hi> they ſeeke not vnto God,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 16.12.</note> but truſt to the <hi>Phyſitian.</hi> In <hi>extreamity of paine,</hi> they ſoone looſe themſelues and their <hi>patience;</hi> like the raging Sea, they vomit out their owne ſhame. In <hi>Death,</hi> they goe away lumpiſhly as <hi>Nabal,</hi> or ridiculouſly, with a <hi>Sardonicall Laughter,</hi> or deſperately, like that Gallant,<note place="margin">M. Perkins in gouernment of the tongue.</note> who ſpurring his Horſſe, till hee ſprang aſide into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as hee was tumbling ouer the Bridge, cryed out; <hi>Horſe, Man, and all to the Diuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:27779:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>All this; is but the beginning of Sorrow:<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 66.24.</note> Death giues them vp to the <hi>Gnawing of that worme which neuer dyet:</hi> the burning of that Lake which ſhall neuer ſlake, and the ſcorching of thoſe flames that ſhall neuer ceaſe. Death cuts off their <hi>Hope,</hi> which endeth with their Life, and giues life to thoſe Torments which ſhall neuer end. Thus is their Life <hi>Miſerable,</hi> their Death <hi>Lamentable,</hi> their End <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt <hi>Grape</hi> which I ſhall plucke from this Goodly Cluſter, and preſſe forth, is, An <hi>Exhortation</hi> to Patience vnder the Croſſe. If <hi>all things ſhall worke for thy Good,</hi> why dooeſt thou murmure and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine againſt God, becauſe hee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes thee with a <hi>Succeſsion</hi> of Croſſes? Thy Afflictions are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great, tedious and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, ſay not thou with <hi>Caine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>My puniſhment is Greater then I can beare,</hi> Geneſ. 4. verſe 13. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer euill it bee that lyes ſo heauie, whether on thy <hi>Bodie, Name,</hi> or
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:27779:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>State,</hi> whether <hi>inward Temptation,</hi> or <hi>outward Tribulations,</hi> is it not for thy <hi>Good?</hi> Wilt thou be ſuch an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy</hi> to thine owne <hi>Soule</hi> as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine at thine <hi>owne Good?</hi> The Cup is bitter; I but happily the leſſe <hi>toothſome,</hi> the more <hi>wholeſome.</hi> Thy teeth are ſet an <hi>edge with eating ſowre Grapes,</hi> this bitter <hi>Aloes</hi> muſt ſet them right. Thou canſt happily make a ſhift to turne ouer a draught of <hi>Worme-wood</hi> Beere euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning next thy heart. Is it not bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as <hi>Gall?</hi> Is it not diſtaſtfull to the <hi>Palate?</hi> Why doeſt thou drinke it? Oh the <hi>Phiſitian</hi> aſſures me it's <hi>for my good.</hi> Thou ſuffereſt the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon</hi> to launce thy raging <hi>vlcer,</hi> to lay a ſharpe <hi>Corazine</hi> which may eate downe the <hi>dead fleſh.</hi> It ſtings cruelly, ſmarts terribly, yet thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureſt it patiently: Why? The <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon</hi> tells thee, <hi>it is good for thee.</hi> If the <hi>Grand Phiſitian</hi> of thy <hi>Soule,</hi> preſcribe a <hi>bitter draught</hi> next thy heart, murmure not; if that skilfull <hi>Soule-Surgeon</hi> clap on a <hi>Coraziue,</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:27779:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> murmure not; hee aſſures thee it's <hi>for thy Good.</hi> Stay not here neither; this will teach thee, to vndergoe thy trouble not onely <hi>patiently,</hi> but <hi>chearefully;</hi> according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Reioyce in Tribulation: Why? Tribulation, brings forth Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; Patience, Experience;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.3.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Hope, that maketh not aſhamed.</hi> Oh the <hi>ſweete Fruite</hi> that growes from this <hi>bitter roote! S.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds <hi>Paul. My Brethren, count it great ioy when you fall into diuers tentations: knowing, that the trying of your faith bringeth foorth Patience;</hi> and let Patience haue her perfect worke. Set before your eyes, that <hi>Mirrour of patience:</hi> remember <hi>Iob</hi> when croſſes came thronging thick and threefold one vpon the necke of another, like a ſhowre of haile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot;<note place="margin">Luke. 21.19.</note> yet the Holy <hi>man poſſeſſes his ſoule by his patience.</hi> Set before you, that <hi>Mirrour of Mirrours,</hi> the <hi>Sauiour of the vvorld;</hi> how willingly did hee drinke of that <hi>bitter Potion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note>
               <note place="margin">Iames. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:27779:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> temptation, for vvhen he is tryed, hee ſhall receiue the Crowne if life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that loue him.</hi> Thou art now in the <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,</hi> waite till the <hi>droſſe</hi> bee conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; thou art now in the <hi>Scouring-houſe,</hi> ſtay till the <hi>ſoile</hi> be wiped off: then ſhalt thou bee tranſlated from this <hi>valley of teares,</hi> to that <hi>Region of ioy;</hi> where all <hi>ſinne</hi> ſhall bee <hi>wiped from thy ſoule,</hi> all <hi>ſorrow from thy heart,</hi> all <hi>teares from thine eyes;</hi> that <hi>ioy</hi> ſhall no man take from thee.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:51"/>
            <head>Gentle Reader, I thought good to fill vp this vacant Page with this Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>All things worke for the beſt to the Godly, whether
<list>
                     <item>Good.
<list>
                           <item>Supreme God, conſider'd in his
<list>
                                 <item>Nature; Atributes.</item>
                                 <item>Workes
<list>
                                       <item>Either of
<list>
                                             <item>Mercy.</item>
                                             <item>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Or
<list>
                                             <item>By meanes</item>
                                             <item>without means.</item>
                                             <item>Againſt means.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate
<list>
                                 <item>Perſons.
<list>
                                       <item>Angels.</item>
                                       <item>Men in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
<list>
                                             <item>Ciuill Magiſtrates.</item>
                                             <item>Eccleſiaſticall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Things.
<list>
                                       <item>Gifts of Minde.</item>
                                       <item>Ornaments of Body.</item>
                                       <item>Gifts of Fortune, ſo termed.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Euill.
<list>
                           <item>Sinne, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<list>
                                 <item>That of our firſt Parents.</item>
                                 <item>That which flows thence
<list>
                                       <item>Originall.</item>
                                       <item>Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.
<list>
                                             <item>Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in the
<list>
                                                   <item>Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</item>
                                                   <item>Errours.</item>
                                                   <item>Will.</item>
                                                   <item>Paſsions.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>groſſer</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<list>
                                 <item>Inward
<list>
                                       <item>Spirituall Diſſertion.</item>
                                       <item>Horror of Conſcience.</item>
                                       <item>Generall—All Affliction.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.
<list>
                                       <item>Priuat euill of
<list>
                                             <item>State, Pouerty,</item>
                                             <item>Name, Ignomy,</item>
                                             <item>Perſons.
<list>
                                                   <item>Diſeaſes</item>
                                                   <item>Death.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>National Plagues.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Publike</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27779:52"/>
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>Gentle Reader, if I ſeeme to breake off abruptly, and to doe my worke by halues; the truth is, my deſire was to preſent this my firſt and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect eſſay to the world for a taſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If it may finde fauour &amp; accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I ſhall be encouraged to perfect what is left vnfiniſhed; if not, little ſaid, ſoone amended.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>For bee, read is. Pag. 1. line 4. for his read this p 3. l. 6. read to p. 4. l. 3. read the crowne. p. 7. l. 10. read <hi>gaſtred.</hi> p. 27. line laſt. read make. p. 44. l. 1. read lockes. p. 51. l. 26. read him p. 56. l. 18. them l. 19. read <hi>Lo-ammi.</hi> p. 64.13.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
